<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Epistle to the authour of the Animadversions upon Fiat lux in excuse and justification of Fiat lux against the said animadversions.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12256027</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12256027</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57490</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57490)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 911:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Epistle to the authour of the Animadversions upon Fiat lux in excuse and justification of Fiat lux against the said animadversions.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Douay? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Index at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>J. V. C. --  (John Vincent Canes), d. 1672. --  Fiat lux.</term>
               <term>Owen, John, 1616-1683. --  Animadversions on a treatise intituled Fiat lux.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57490:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE TO The Authour Of the ANIMADVERSIONS UPON <hi>FIAT L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>X.</hi> In excuſe and juſtification of <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> againſt the ſaid Animadverſions.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 120.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Quid detur tibi aut quid apponatur tibi ad lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam doloſam?</l>
               <l>Sagittae potentis acutae, cum carbonibus deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriis.</l>
               <l>Cùm his qui oderunt pacem eram pacificus: cùm loquebar illis impugnabant me gratis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="animadversions">
            <pb facs="tcp:57490:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57490:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the Author of the Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon <hi>Fiat Lux.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Was in my Journey in the North, far enough from <hi>London,</hi> when your <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions</hi> upon <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> came forth. Nor did I ever ſet eye upon them, till my return in <hi>February,</hi> about half a year after: which I tell you Sir, to excuſe my ſilence. And now in brief: For your labour I thank you; for your endeavour I pitty you; for your purpoſe I pardon you: that being as I beleev, intended for Gentlemens ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the other for <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> his confutation, this for the <hi>Authours</hi> confuſion.</p>
            <p>I may not go about to reply unto you; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus this would be againſt the very end and principles of <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> it ſelf, which ſpeaks forth nothing more then this, That Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies about Religion are vain and fruitles. And leſt this ſhould not be able to detain me from any ſuch reply, you adde your own threats, <hi>That if I ſhall dare to write again, you will make me know</hi> what manner of man you are. However Sir, let me crave leave to thank
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57490:3"/>you for the paſtime your <hi>Animadverſions</hi> have given me ſince my return.</p>
            <p>But Sir, you miſtake the very drift and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> which makes you to erre ever and anon, and almoſt continually throughout your whole Book, whiles you take that as ſpoken abſolutely which is only ſaid upon an <hi>hypotheſis</hi> of our preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here in <hi>England,</hi> which is diſtraction, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, and wars, in order to a contrary end of unity, love, and concord, deſigned by <hi>Fiat Lux.</hi> By vertue of this capital miſtake, what by me is ſaid of the obſcurity of God, Nature, and Providence, is with you impertinent; that of Light and Spirit, impious; that of Plea of Parties, frivolous; that of Reaſon, diſſonant and to no purpos; that of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture blaſphemous; that of the Hiſtory of Religion, no leſs inconſequent than untrue. In a word, this thing, that thing, every thing, a wilde, diſhoneſt illiterate diſcours.</p>
            <p>Some would wonder, that he who writes in conſutation of a Book, ſhould be himſelf the only man that underſtands it not? But the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is apparent: It is your only advantage to miſtake. The whole diſcours of <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> chained together, one part with another, from that which is ſuppoſed to that which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, would breath ſo much of charity and ſobernes, that my <hi>Commentatour</hi> could not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57490:3"/>have told how to make <hi>any mad verſions</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p>It is not yet too late. Now that you have finiſhed your <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> or Comment, or Notes upon it, you may do well to take my Book again into your hands, read it calmly, and underſtand it.</p>
            <p>That which you ſpeak ſo frequently of <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> his ignorance, is not altogether amiſs: for he pretends not much to learning, although he knows what he ſayes. But yet Sir, if you had defied and villified him with leſs violence, and more ſeldom, and not ſo univerſally in every point of Hiſtory, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and Philoſophy, nor juſt then when you had leaſt caus, it had been more for your honour.</p>
            <p>And in my minde you too much forget your ſelf, when you recount ſo often with regret and anger, that ſom Gentlemen of the Land ſhould it ſeems, through their own inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, have any liking of a Book which you judg ſo ſlight, aiery, vain, fallacious, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: As if they had none, and you all the judgment of diſcerning. Gentlemen, Sir, muſt be allowed a ſens of Religion as well as Miniſters; and their portion of reaſon muſt not therfor be leſs, becaus their Blood is more noble, the company they keep more accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht, and their education better. They have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57490:4"/>the body, although they wear not the Cloak of Religion; and maſters they are of their own reaſon, though not of yours. This is one difference between Catholick Countreyes and ours, that there the Clergy man is only regarded for his vertue, and the power he hath received, or is at leaſt believed to have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from God in the great miniſtery of our Reconciliation. And if he have any additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of learning beſides, it is looked upon as a good accidental Ornament, but not as any eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential complement of his Profeſſion: ſo that it often happens without any wonderment at all, that the Gentleman Patron is the learned man, and the Prieſt his Chaplain of little or no ſcience in compariſon; but here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> our Gentlemen are diſparaged by their own Black Coats, and not ſuffered to uſe their judgments in any kinde of learning, without a gibe from them. The Gentleman is reaſonles, and the ſcribling Caſſock is the only Schollar: he alone muſt ſpeak all, know all, and only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</p>
            <p>I cannot but ſmile to ſee you turn ſo dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly every thing that is ſaid in <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> to your own uſe. His diſcours of innocence and moderation, gives you occaſion to ſpeak and amply dilate of wars, murders, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, lyes, hypocriſies, villanies: And when he cries, <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> it is motive enough for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57490:4"/>you to cry, <hi>Guns</hi> and <hi>Daggers.</hi> You rave and rage againſt him and the whole earth, you load your pen and pages with the tyrannies, deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, diſorders have been aforetime in the world, not heeding that you had not ſo much as heard at this day of any ſuch abuſes, if their holy and renowned Clergy-men, who ſtill declaimed againſt the vices of their times, had not left them upon record, or ſo much as conſidering, that even now in theſe beſt times of Reformation are as grand diſorders in all kindes as ever were in the worſt times of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh corruption: nay there was never any crow or magpy ſo pecked and cawed upon the back of a ſheep, as you do upon <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> and if he do but ſtir or wag, you threaten, if I underſtand you right, to peck out his eyes. And all this, becauſe <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> indeavours to ſhow, that animoſities about matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are groundleſs, prejudicial to peace and neighbourhood, ruinous, deſolatory, endles, and conſequently vain, fruitles, and ſinful, (ther may indeed be ſom advantage on the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants ſide, which is not in the Plaintiff or Actour, but this at preſent I am not to take notice of) nay finally, that they have ever don much harm in Kingdoms, but never good. In all this Sir, you do like your ſelf, you love nois and whirlwinds, and when you hear of <hi>Peace,</hi> prepare your ſelf to <hi>Battle:</hi> ſo ill do you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57490:5"/>the ſound of a retreat, or, becaus it ſuits not with your ends and inclinations, will not.</p>
            <p>But all this diſcours of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> tends, ſay you, to <hi>Popery.</hi> A fearful thing, and ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful news to Miniſters; for whoſe fooliſh, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and ungrounded quarrels, we have lately engaged our honour, peace, livelihood, lives, and all that is dear unto us; and yet we are ſtill, but where we were before we began: nay, ten times farther off from any reconcilement, unity, or ſatisfaction then before? And ſuch ſucceſs have all wars ever had, where the alarm was given in the Pulpit. But why muſt it tend to Popery? Becaus <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> is bold to ſay, that <hi>Popery</hi> in its own likenes is not ſo ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as we imagin it. Lord! what a ſtrange thing is this, that either <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> or any els ſhould preſume to ſay, that we in <hi>England,</hi> or other Nations may be carried by the reports of ſom intereſted men, to think wors of a thing then it may deſerv; eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we com all to Church to hear Gods Word, and there meet with a man, who in the firſt opening of his lips, cryes, <hi>Hearken my Beloved to the word of the Lord;</hi> and ſo having with that airy hony-comb ſweetned the edges of our ears, pours into them afterward what poiſon of his own conceived intereſts he pleaſes; all which we his <hi>dearly beloved</hi> let
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57490:5"/>down greedily into our hearts, as that preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous word of the Lord, which he at firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed. By which fallacies, we have been in the time of theſe our late wars, ſo far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigled (I ſpeak to men now alive, who all know I ſpeak true) that it became then a moſt dangerous thing, yea, treaſon it ſelf, to ſay, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> who was by this our Pulpit rhetorick made as odious then through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Land, as Popery, what ever it be, ever was or can be? And are not neighbours thus abuſed daily almoſt in every thing? where is that man who hath not by ſuch like means been one time or other induced, to think amiſs, even of his moſt innocent and deareſt friends, till himſelf by trial found the contrary. <hi>O but God forbid,</hi> you will ſay, <hi>that ever we ſhould com by trial to know what Popery is.</hi> Sir, may it be far from us, ſo long as heaven pleaſes: But i'th interim, what harm can it be to us to mitigate our paſſions! which if there be no miſtake, are prejudicial notwithſtanding to our own peace; and if a miſtake there ſhould be, are double injurious, and deſperately ſinful before God and man. <hi>Oh but miſtake there can be none!</hi> Sir, let me tell you roundly. By your own Book of <hi>Animadverſions</hi> I do as clearly ſee, as ever I beheld Sun in the Firmament, that you do not your ſelf underſtand what <hi>Popery</hi> is; even no more, then the pooreſt meaneſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57490:6"/>peaſant in the Pariſh. But who is able to make this good and clear unto you? no body Sir, ſo long as you are in paſſion; in a calm of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, your very ſelf. Nor could I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that ſerenity, have been ever able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern it. But yet, there is one thing more, which will hinder your acknowledgment, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you ſhould com to know it. It is their intereſt to juſtify themſelvs, and yours to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them.</p>
            <p>Had not you with your threats ſo much frighted me from any thought of writing any more, I could I think my ſelf (who am in your judgement one of the greateſt ingrams in the Land) make it yet appear that the preſent Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Religion, if to pleas you they will give me leav to call it ſo, is not only leſs ugly then we conceive it, but far more innocent and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then I have made it. And, if ther were not ſo much as one Catholik, or Romaniſt, or Papiſt upon earth, yet ſo far am I from any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt herin, that in that judgment I would not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding dy alone. Nor had I ſet before my eyes any other end in that my <hi>Fiat</hi> of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, againſt which you write your hot <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> then the peace and welfar of my Countrey, which under the pretended ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Popery, inflamed by the alarms of <hi>Vicars</hi> and their <hi>Wives,</hi> for whom we fight as it were <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> hates and miſchiefs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57490:6"/>ſtrikes and deſtroyes one another without end. And yet (which is a ſtrange thing) whilſt every one conceits himſelf to fight for <hi>Purity</hi> of Goſpel againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> they fight all for <hi>Popery</hi> againſt <hi>Purity</hi> of Goſpel. And this you cannot deny, if you will but aver what in your Book of <hi>Animadverſions</hi> you do your ſelf ſo frequently aſſert, that what good ſoever the <hi>Papiſts</hi> or Roman Catholiks either do or have amongſt them, they have and do the ſame as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and not as <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and that Popery is it ſelf nothing els, but pride, intereſt, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, tyranny, worldly reſpects, thirſt of blood, affectation of Dominion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As on the other ſide, grace charity and peace is, I am ſure, the pure quinteſſence of Goſpel, and the very extract of true Religion. Either then I had reaſon to tell you, that you underſtand not what <hi>Popery</hi> is; or if you do, you muſt needs acknowledge, that thoſe who here in <hi>England</hi> betwixt the years of 1640. and 1660. with guns and daggers, as you often phraſe it, with field rhetorick and pulpit cannon, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted all before them, even Church and State too, let them call themſelvs <hi>Puritans, Independents, Presbyterians,</hi> or what they pleas, were all of them by this your own rule, as <hi>arch Papiſts</hi> as ever trode upon the earth. Nor is it of concernment, ſo they have the reality of the thing, whence they may borrow their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57490:7"/>name; whether ſome man upon earth be their <hi>Pope,</hi> or whether the <hi>Devil</hi> be himſelf their ghoſtly father.</p>
            <p>And I fear Sir (give me leave to expreſs my fears) I do very deeply fear, that you wer your ſelf ſome part of that diſmal tempeſt, which in the laſt years of our woful <hi>Anarchy</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore all before it, not only Church and State, but reaſon, right, honeſty, all true Religion, and even good natur too. The very flaſhings of your pen move me to this thought. The whole phyſiognomy of your Book ſpeaks the hot and fiery ſpirit of the Authour. Firſt, you cannot abide to hear of <hi>moderation,</hi> it is with you moſt wicked, hypocritical, and devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, eſpecially as it coms from me. And for this one thing <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> ſuffers more from you, then for all the contents of the Book put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. My reaſon is your paſſion; my mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration inflames your wrath; and you are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for ſtark wild, becaus I utter ſo much of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety. Secondly, your ſo frequent talking of <hi>ſword and blood, fire and faggot, guns and dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> do more then ſhow, you have not yet let go thoſe hot and furious imaginations. And in a phrenſy you upbraid your adverſary with that, which ſucceeded not as you would have had it in your ſelf. Thirdly, your prophetick <hi>aſſurance</hi> ſo often inculcated, that if <hi>you could but once com to whiſper me in the ear, I would
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57490:7"/>plainly acknowledg, either that I underſtand not myſelf what I ſay, or if I do, beleev it not,</hi> givs a fair character of thoſe fanatick times, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ignorance and hypocriſy prevailed over worth and truth; wherof if your ſelf wer any part, it is no wonder you ſhould think that I or any man els, ſhould either ſpeak he knows not what, or beleev not what himſelf ſpeaks. It was the proper badg of thoſe times; when after the alarm ſounded in the Pulpit, that our people therupon went forth in troops to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, neither did the peaſant underſtand nor the man in black beleev, although the ſound rung generally in their ears, that it was <hi>the ſword of the Lord and of Gideon,</hi> which they brandiſht againſt the loyal band, their foes. Fourthly, your pert aſſertion ſo often occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in your Book, that <hi>ther is neither reaſon, truth, nor honeſty in my words,</hi> is but the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of that former intemperat zeal: and the more frequent it occurs, the leſs approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it will find. Fiftly, your ſharp and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent menaces, that if I write or ſpeak again, <hi>I ſhall hear more, finde more, feel more, more to my ſmart, more then I imagin, more then I would,</hi> relliſhes too much of that inſulting humour our poor bleeding Land then groaned under, the many years of our anarchical confuſion. Sixtly, the abſence of your <hi>name</hi> in the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpiece of your book, which I have never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57490:8"/>obſerved in all my life of any Proteſtant writer, that hath ever in my time ſet forth a book here in <hi>England</hi> againſt Popery, givs no ſmall ſuſpicion that the Authour of our <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions</hi> is no ſuch <hi>Proteſtant</hi> as he would be thought to be. Laſtly, that I may omit other ſpecial reaſons, your other general trick of charging me then moſt of all with <hi>fraud, ignorance, and wickednes,</hi> when in your own heart you find me moſt clear from any ſuch blemiſh, thereby to put a vail upon your own caus, which would otherways be diſparaged, makes me ſmell a fox, a notorious one; <hi>ſic no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes.</hi> This has been too often acted here in <hi>England</hi> to be ſoon forgotten. The better the cauſe, the lowder ſtill was the cry againſt thoſe who ſtood for it, that the bluſtering nois of calumnies might drown all report of their innocence. And by all this I cannot Sir but ſuſpect, that if the deſcription of Popery your Animadverſions gives us, be right, you are a Papiſt your ſelf, a great one, and no true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. But as it is, ſo let it be.</p>
            <p>Thus much I only tell you, that you may ſee I am neither neglective of your book, nor idle; but have peruſed and read it over. And although what for the threats of your <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions,</hi> and what for the reaſons of my own <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> I may not enter into contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies: yet I hope I may let you know that I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57490:8"/>have ſeen your work. And that you may the better credit me, I will give you a ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, firſt in general, then in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</p>
            <p>All the whole deſign of <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> you do utterly miſtake, throughout all your book of <hi>Animadverſions;</hi> ſo that you conceiv that to be a Controverſy, which is none; that to be abſolutely aſſerted, which is but hypothetical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſed; that to be only for one ſide, which is indifferently for all; although I ſpeak moſt for them that are moſt ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and am in very deed abſolutely againſt all ſpeaking, quarrelling, diſputing about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If you will but have patience to hear my purpoſe and deſign, which to all men not intereſted and blinded with a prejudice, is clear enough relucent in the whole context of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> what I ſay will eaſily appear to your ſelf. <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> ſayes one thing, and ſuppoſes it, another thing he deſires and aims at: that he diſlikes, this commends. We are at this day at variance about Religion, this <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> ſuppoſes? but it were better to have peace, this he aims at and deſires. And both theſe things are intermingled up and down in my Book, according to that ſmall faculty that God hath given me, though not according to the uſual method of Books now adayes. Here Sir in few words you have the whole ſumme
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57490:9"/>of <hi>Fiat Lux.</hi> And I hope you will grant that that to be the ſcope of my book, which I made it for. That we are now at varience is moſt clear and certain, by me ſuppoſed, and not to be denied. And that it were better to have peace, is as abſolutely expedient, as the other is evidently true. Theſe then being things both of them which no man can reſiſt; either by denying the one, or diſliking the other; I thought them better intermingled than ſet apart, and with more reaſon to be ſuppoſed then induſtriouſly proved. Yet to ſuperinduce a diſpoſition unto peace, my only work was to demonſtrate an uſeleſnes, an endleſnes, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitablenes of quarrels, which I laboured quite through my book, beginning it with an intimation of our quarrels, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the fruits and works of the fleſh; and ending it with a commendation of charity, which is the great fruit and bleſſing of Gods holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Now the eaſier to perſwade my Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to a belief both of the one and the other; firſt, is inſinuated in <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> both the ill grounds and worſt effects of feuds; then is the plea of parties ſpecified; their probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities acknowledged; and laſtly an impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ever bringing our debates to a concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either by light, or ſpirit, reaſon or ſcriptur texts, ſo long as we ſtand ſeparated from any ſuperiour judicative power unto which all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57490:9"/>parties will ſubmit, is I think with a ſtrong probability, if not demonſtrative evidence concluded. And therfor is it thought by <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> to be more rational and Chriſtian like, to leav theſe endles, groundles, and ruinous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; and reſign our ſelvs to humility and peace. This is the deſign and whole ſumm of my book. And although I ſpeak up and down here for <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ther for <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> elſwhere for <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Independents,</hi> commonly out of the very diſcourſes they make for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, yet do I not defend either their wayes or their arguments. Nor do I teach any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin at all, or hold there any opinion; but only giv to underſtand in that one little book, what is largely diſcourſed in a hundred; That all parties do make out to themſelves ſuch a probability, which as it ſtands joyned with the actours reſolution, and ſeparated from any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour viſible power to which they will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, can never be ſubdued. And hath not long experience proved this as true as any thing els? What is ther in <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> that can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied? Is it not evident that we are now at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance? and too long indeed have been. Is it not alſo clear, that peace, charity, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood is better than variance, diſſention, and wars? do not parties ſtrongly plead for themſelvs, ſo far perſwaded each one that he is in the right, that he will not yield that truth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57490:10"/>is with any but himſelf. Is not all this evident? I am ſure it is; and all <hi>England</hi> will witnes it. And if any one ſhould be able to evince, that any reaſonings made in <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> either for <hi>Papiſts, Proteſtants,</hi> or others, be not certain, or perhaps not probable, yet he does nothing, except he be able to prove likewiſe, that they are not probable to <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> or to thoſe that uſe them, whether <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or <hi>Papiſts;</hi> which he can no more do, than he can pull a ſtar out of the firmament. I ſay Sir again, and mark I pray you what I ſay: If you ſhould chance to evince, that the reaſons brought by <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> either for the doctrin or practiſes of Papiſts or others, be either not probable or untrue, yet is your labour all in vain, except you be able to demonſtrate likewiſe, that they are not probable to <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> or to Papiſts and others who uſe thoſe reaſons: which you can no more do, then any thing that is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely impoſſible. By this time Sir, you may diſcern how hard it is to deal with <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> and impoſſible to confute him: ſith he ſpeaks nothing, but what is as clearly true and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as what we ſee at mid-day. Nor do I in this any way exalt the ability of the Authour, whom you are pleaſed ſo much and frequently to diſable. A Tomfool may ſay that, which all the wiſe men in the world cannot gain-ſay: as he did, who ſaid the Sun was above half an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57490:10"/>hour high at noon. It was <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune rather then chois, to utter words which will no ſooner be read than acknowledged. And it was your misfortune Sir, to employ your greater talents in refuding evident truths, perhaps for no other reaſon, but becaus they iſſued from the pen of a man, who is not ſo great a friend to faction as you could wiſh. And although you proceed very harſh and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly; yet am I verily perſwaded, you now diſcern, though too late for your credit, that you had all this while, according to our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh proverb, good Mr. Doctor, a wrong ſow by the ear. Thus far in general. Now briefly to give you ſom account in particular.</p>
            <p>You ſpend four Chapters and a hundred and eighteen pages, which is the fourth part of your Book, before you com to the firſt line and paragraff of mine, <hi>The applaus and honour of this world, &amp;c,</hi> And it is not unwittily done. For being to be led, as you heavily complain, out of your ordinary road of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, by the wilde chaſe of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> it behoved you to draw ſom general common places of your own, for your ſelf to walk in, and exerciſe your rhetorick and anger, before you purſue a bird that flies not, you ſay, in any uſual tract.</p>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>Preface from page <hi>1,</hi> to page <hi>19</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your preface, wherein you ſpeak of my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57490:11"/>ſubtilty and your own pretence, affords me no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the beginning of your miſtake, which will run quite through your book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>1</hi> Chap. from page <hi>19.</hi> to <hi>29.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your firſt Chapter beats me about the pate, for ſaying that I conceal my method, with a terrible ſyllogiſtical <hi>dilemma, He that uſeth no method,</hi> ſay you, <hi>cannot conceal it,</hi> and <hi>if he hath concealed it, he hath uſed one.</hi> But I muſt paſs by ſtore of ſuch doughty ſtuff, being only fit for the young <hi>Oxford</hi> Schollar, who being com home to take air, would prove before his father and mother, that two eggs were three. Then going on you deny, that <hi>Proteſtants ever oppoſed the merit of good works;</hi> which at firſt I wondered at, ſeeing the ſound of it has rung ſo often in mine own ears, and ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred books written in this laſt age, ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently witnes it in all places, till I found after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in my thorow peruſal of your book, that you neither heed what you ſay, or how much you deny. At laſt giving a diſtinction of the <hi>intrinſick acceptability of our works,</hi> the eaſlier to ſilence me, you ſay as I ſay.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> Chap. from page <hi>29.</hi> to <hi>110.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your ſecond chapter collects out of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> as you ſay, ten general concluſions, ſpread all over like veins and arteries, in the body of that my book. And this you do that you may make your ſelf a <hi>campus Martius</hi> to ſport in,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57490:11"/>without confinement to my method. But you name not any page of my book where thoſe principles may all or any of them be found; and you do wiſely; for in the ſens thoſe words do either naturally make out, or in which you underſtand them, of all the whole ten I can hardly own any one. The firſt of my princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples muſt be this, <hi>That we received the Goſpel firſt from</hi> Rome. We, that is, we Engliſh firſt received it thence. But againſt this you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>That we received it not firſt from Rome, but by Joſeph of Arimathea from Paleſtin, as Fiat Lux himſelf acknowledges.</hi> Sir, if <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> ſay both theſe things, he cannot mean in your contradictory fals ſens, but in his own true one: We, that is, we Engliſhmen, the now actual inhabitants of this Land, and progeny of the Saxons, received firſt our Goſpel and Chriſtendom from <hi>Rome,</hi> though the Brittans that inhabited this Land before, differing as much from us as <hi>Antipodes,</hi> had ſome of them been Chriſtened long before us. And yet the Chriſtendom that prevailed and laſted among the Brittans, even they alſo as well as we, had it from <hi>Rome</hi> too, mark this likewiſe. But you reply, <hi>Though perſons from Rome did firſt plant Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity among the Saxons, was it the Popes Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion they taught? did the Pope firſt finde it out? or did they Baptiſe in the name of the Pope?</hi> Good Sir, it was the Popes Religion, not invented,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57490:12"/>but profeſt by him, and from him derived unto us by his miſſioners. You adde, <hi>Did not the Goſpel come to Rome as well as to us? for it was not firſt preached there.</hi> Sir, properly ſpeaking, it came not ſo to <hi>Rome</hi> as it came to us. For one of the twelve fountains, nay two of the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, and thoſe the largeſt and greateſt was transferred to <hi>Rome,</hi> which they watered with their blood: we had never any ſuch ſtanding fountain of our Chriſtian Religion here, but only a ſtream derived to us from thence.</p>
               <p>My ſecond aſſertion muſt be, <hi>From whom we firſt received our Religion, with them we muſt ſtill abide.</hi> This principle as it is never deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> though you put it upon me, ſo is it in the latitude it carries, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you underſtand it, abſolutely fals, never thought of by me, and indeed impoſſible; for how can we abide with them in any truth, who may perhaps not abide in it themſelvs. Great part of <hi>Flanders</hi> was firſt converted by Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen, and yet are they not obliged, either by <hi>Fiat Lux</hi> or any <hi>lux</hi> whatſoever, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Engliſh in our now preſent wayes.</p>
               <p>My third is, <hi>The Roman Religion is ſtill the ſame?</hi> This indeed: though I do no where formally expreſs it, yet I ſuppoſe it, becaus I know it hath been demonſtratively proved a hundred times over. You deny it has been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, why do you not then diſprove it? becaus,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57490:12"/>
                  <hi>you decline,</hi> ſay you, <hi>all common places:</hi> very good, ſo do I; let us com then to proper ones. You fall then upon my Queries in the end of my book. <hi>The Roman was once a true flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church, and if ſhe ever fell, ſhe muſt fall either by apoſtacy, hereſy, or ſchiſm, &amp;c.</hi> So I ſpeak there. And to this you reply, that <hi>the Church that then was in the Apoſtles time, was indeed true, not that Roman Church that now is.</hi> So, ſo; then ſay I, that former true Church muſt fall then, ſom time or other; when did ſhe fall? and how did ſhe fall? by apoſtacy, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, or ſchiſm? <hi>Perhaps,</hi> ſay you, <hi>neither way: for ſhe might fall by an earthquake.</hi> Sir we ſpeak not here of any cauſal or natural downfal or death of mortals by plague, famine or earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, but a moral and voluntary laps in faith. What do you ſpeak to me of earthquakes! you adde therfor the ſecond time, that <hi>ſhe might fall by idolatry; and ſo neither by apoſtacy, hereſy, or ſchiſm.</hi> Good Sir, idolatry is a mixt miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour both in faith and manners, I ſpeak of the ſingle one of faith. And he that falls by ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, if he keep ſtill ſome parts of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty entire, he falls by hereſy; by apoſtacy, if he keep none. At laſt finding your ſelf puſled, in the third place you lay on load; <hi>She fell,</hi> ſay you, <hi>by apoſtacy, idolatry, hereſy, ſchiſme, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſnes, and prophanenes of life.</hi> And in this you do, not much unlike the drunken youth,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57490:13"/>who being bid to hit his maſters finger with his, when he perceived he could not do it, he ran his whole fiſt againſt it. But did ſhe fall by apoſtacy? <hi>By a partial one,</hi> ſay you, <hi>not a total one.</hi> Good ſir, in this diviſion, apoſtaſy is ſet to expres a total relaps; in oppoſition to hereſy, which is the partial. Did ſhe then fall by hereſy, in adhering to any error in faith, contrary to the approved doctrin of the Church? Here you ſmile ſeriouſly, and tell me, that <hi>ſince I take the Roman and catholik Church to be one, ſhe could not indeed adhere to any thing but what ſhe did adhere unto.</hi> Sir, I take them indeed to be one, but here I ſpeak <hi>ad bominem,</hi> to one that does not take them ſo. And then, if indeed the Roman Church had ever ſwerved in faith, as you ſay ſhe has, and be her ſelf but as an other ordinary particular Church, as you ſay ſhe is; then might you find ſome one or other more general Church, if any ther were, to judg her, ſom Oecumenical councel to condemn her, ſom fathers either greek or latin, expreſly to write againſt her, as Proteſtants now do, ſom or other grave ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn autority to cenſur her; or at leaſt ſom company of beleevers out of whoſe body ſhe went, and from whoſe faith ſhe fell: none of which ſince you are not able to aſſign, my Query remains unanſwered, and the Roman ſtill as flouriſhing a Church, as ever ſhe was.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57490:13"/>
               <p>The fourth aſſertion, <hi>frequently,</hi> ſay you, <hi>pleaded by our Authour is; that all things as to religion were ever quiet and in peace, before the Proteſtants relinquiſhment of the Roman Sea.</hi> This principle you pretend is drawn out of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> not becaus it is there; but only to open a door for your ſelf, to expatiate into ſom wide general diſcours, about the many wars, diſtractions, and factious altercations, that hav been aforetime up and down the world, in ſom ſeveral ages of Chriſtianity: And you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for ſay <hi>it is frequently pleaded by me,</hi> becaus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I never ſpeak one word of it. And it is in truth a fals and fond aſſertion. Though neither you nor I can deny, that ſuch as keep unity of faith with that Church, can never ſo long as they hold it, fall out upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>Fift is, <hi>that the firſt reformers were moſt of them contemptible perſons, their means indirect, and ends ſiniſter.</hi> Where is it ſir, where is it, that I meddle with any mens perſons, or ſay they are contemptible. What and how many are theſe perſons, and where did they live? But this you adde of your own, in a vaſt uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal notion, to the end you may bring in the apoſtles and prophets, and ſom kings, into the liſt of perſons by me ſurnamed contemptible, and liken my ſpeech, who never ſpeak any ſuch thing, to the ſarcaſms of <hi>Celſus, Lucian, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiry,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57490:14"/>Julian,</hi> and other Pagans. So likewiſe in the very beginning of this your ſecond cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter you ſpend four leaves in a paralel betwixt me and the Pagan <hi>Celſus,</hi> wherof ther is not any one member of it true. <hi>Doth Fiat Lux,</hi> ſay you, <hi>lay the caus of all the troubles, diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, tumults, wars within the Nations of Europ upon the Proteſtants? Doth he charg the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants that by their ſchiſms and ſeditions they make a way for other revolts? doth he gather a rapſody of inſignificant words? doth he inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their diviſions; doth he mannage the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Jews againſt Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſo doth Celſus, who is confuted by learned Origen,</hi> &amp;c. Where does <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> where does, does he, does he any ſuch thing. Are you not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to talk at this rate. I give a hint indeed of the diviſions that be amongſt us, and the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent argumentations that are made to imbroil and puſle one another, with our much evil and little appearance of any good, in order to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and peace, which is the end of my diſcours. But muſt I therfor be <hi>Celſus?</hi> Did <hi>Celſus</hi> do any ſuch thing to ſuch an end? It is the end that moraliſes and ſpecifies the action. To diminiſh Chriſtianity by upbraiding our frailties is paganiſh: to exhort to unity by repreſenting the inconvenience of faction is a Chriſtian and pious work. When honeſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in the Pulpit ſpeak ten times more
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57490:14"/>full and vehemently againſt the diviſions, wars and contentions that be amongſt us, than ever came into my thoughts; muſt they therfor be, every one of them a <hi>Celſus,</hi> a pagan <hi>Celſus?</hi> what ſtuff is this! But it is not only my defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation you aim at, your own glory coms in the reer. If I be <hi>Celſus,</hi> the pagan <hi>Celſus,</hi> then muſt you forſooth be <hi>Origen</hi> that wrote againſt him, honeſt <hi>Origen.</hi> That is the thing. Pray ſir, it is but a word, let me advice you by the way, that you do not forget your ſelf in your heat, and give your wife occaſion to fall out with you. However you may, yet will not ſhe like it perhaps ſo well, that her husband ſhould be <hi>Origen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My ſixt principle muſt be, <hi>that our departure from Rome hath been the caus of all our evils.</hi> This is but the ſame with the fourth, in other words, but added for one to make up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and it is, you ſay, <hi>every where ſpread over the face of Fiat Lux.</hi> Sir you may ſay what you pleas to be in his face, but I know beſt what is in the heart and bowels both of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> and his authour. And ſure I am this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came into my thoughts. Our diſſentions in faith may well multiply, as we ſee with our eyes they do, by our further departur from unity; and this may caus much evil. But the branches of our too too manifold evils found among the ſons of men, ſpread all, as <hi>Fiat Lux</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57490:15"/>alſo ſpeaks, from that fertil root of our innate concupiſcence, which by evil cuſtoms riſes up into a thick bole of vitious inclinations, while we ſtudy not to impair but rather to augment and nouriſh it. However I muſt give you leav to number this among my ſilly principles, to the end you may talk more copiouſly of the diſputes, and wars and broils that are and have been in ſeveral parts of Chriſtendom, and fall again into your much affected and often itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted rhetorical ſtrain, <hi>So the Pagans judged the Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Seventh is, <hi>There is no remedy of our evils, but by a returnal to the Roman Sea.</hi> This and the principle foregoing, had not you warily cloven a hair, had been all one; and both are equally mine. But ſir, that may remedy our difference in faith, which neither can nor will prevent varieties in philoſophy or other world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judgements: nor conſidering the infinite diverſity of mens humours, is there any one thing equally prevalent with all men, and at all times, to the like good effect, and if it do certainly help one evil, it is not therfor a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for all. But it ſeems you have yet a little more mirth and choller to vent, and therfor I muſt permit you to adde this principle for mine, that you may ſmilingly conſider, how the Romans ſhould cure our evils, that cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent diſorders differences and ſins amongſt themſelvs.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57490:15"/>
               <p>The eight follows, <hi>That Scriptur on ſundry accounts is inſufficient to ſettle us in the truth.</hi> And in this you flouriſh and triumph moſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly for fifteen pages together, as the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of the word of God. But ſir, you ſpeak not one word to the purpos, or againſt me at all, if I had delivered any ſuch principle. Gods word is both the ſufficient and only neceſſary means both of our converſion and ſettlement as well in truth as vertue. But ſir, the thing you heed not, and unto which I onely ſpeak, is this: If the ſcripture be in two hands, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Proteſtant Church in <hi>England,</hi> and of the Puritan who with that ſcriptur roſe up and rebelled againſt her, can the ſcriptur alone of it ſelſ decide the buſines, how ſhall it do it, has it ever don it? or can that written word now ſolitary and in private hands ſo ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle any in a way that neither himſelf, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent adherents, nor future generations ſhall queſtion it, or with as much probability diſſent from it either totally or in part, as himſelf firſt ſet it. This ſir is the caſe, unto which you do neither here nor in all your whole book ſpeak one word. And what you ſpeak otherwis of the ſcripturs excellency, I allow it for good. What is not againſt me, is with me.</p>
               <p>Ninth, <hi>The Pope is a good man and ſeeks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but our good.</hi> This alſo I no where aver. For I never ſaw him, nor have any ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57490:16"/>with him, as to know whether he be a good man or no, though in charity I do not uſe to iudg hardly of any body. Much leſs could I ſay, that he whom I know to have a general ſolicitude for all Churches, ſeeks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but our good. Sir, if I had pondred my words in <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> no better than you heed yours in your <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon it, they might even go together both of them to lap pepper and ſpices, or ſom other yet more vile emploiment.</p>
               <p>Tenth, that <hi>the devotion of Catholiks far tranſcends that of Proteſtants.</hi> But ſir I never made in <hi>Fiat lux</hi> any compariſon between their devotions; nor can I ſay how much the one is, or how little the other. But you are the maddeſt <hi>Commentatour</hi> I have ever ſeen, you firſt make the <hi>Text,</hi> and then <hi>Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> upon it. Here at length you conclude your chapter, and <hi>would,</hi> ſay you, <hi>your book al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; if you had none to deal with but ingenious and judicious readers.</hi> It ſeems what follows, is for readers neither judicious nor ingenious. And becaus I knew you took me for one of thoſe, I went on in my view. Indeed, had I not undertaken to give you an account of your whole book, I could have been well content to ſtop here with ingenious and judicious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and look no further. Doubtles in this affair good wits will jump. You would write
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57490:16"/>no more had you none but judicious readers, and theſe will read no more becaus they are judicious. But I poor aſs muſt jogge on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>3</hi> ch. from page <hi>110</hi> to <hi>119.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your third chapter concerns my preface, which in part you allow, and partly diſlike. And I am equally content with both.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> or <hi>5</hi> ch. from page <hi>119</hi> to <hi>148.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your fourth chapter by miſtake of preſs is named Fift, and ſo I muſt here call it. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins my book, and takes up five of my para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffs at once, You have loitered long about the gate like a trifling idlesbee, and mean now it ſeems, when you com to my own words, to go nimbly over them, as of leſſer concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then your own foreſtalled conceits, which you have hitherto made ſport with. You firſt ſet up a maypole and then danced about it, and now at length half tired and almoſt out of breath, you come home to me.</p>
               <p>My firſt paragraff about <hi>Diverſity of feuds</hi> you do not much except againſt. But I ſee you do not affect the <hi>ſchoolmen,</hi> haply for the ſame reaſon the French love not <hi>Talbot,</hi> having been uſed in their infancy to be frighted with that name. However you think I have good reaſon to make honourable mention of them, becaus <hi>they were,</hi> ſay you, <hi>the hammerers and forgers of Popery.</hi> Alas ſir, I ſee that anger ſpoils your memory; for in the twelfth and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57490:17"/>thirteenth chapter of that very book of your <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> you make <hi>Popery</hi> to be ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mered and forged not a few hundreds of years, before any <hi>ſchoolmen</hi> were extant. You check me alſo for ſaying, that reformation of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is pretended by emulous Plebeians, <hi>as though</hi> ſay you, <hi>Hezekiah, Joſiah, and other good Kings and Princes alſo of our own were emulous plebeians.</hi> But ſir, when I ſay in <hi>Fiat lux</hi> p. 20. <hi>what glory the emulous plebeian ſees given to higher ſpirits,</hi> &amp;c. I only ſpeak of the times of vulgar inſurrection againſt autority; as all men ſee except your ſelf, who will not.</p>
               <p>My ſecond paragraff of the <hi>Ground of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels</hi> you like well, and explicate it with a text to help me out. I could not haply tell, how to cite <hi>James,</hi> the fourth chapter, the firſt and ſecond vers of that chapter, without your help. However, it is kindnes though it be but cours, as ſir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> told his maid, when ſhe kiſt him as he was going to execution; and ſo I take it.</p>
               <p>My third paragraff about <hi>nullity of title</hi> would, you think, every period of it confute my ſelf. But that ſaying of S. <hi>Paul, An à vobis verbum Dei proceſſit an ad vos ſolos pervenit,</hi> which I make uſe of to ſtop the mouth of all vitilitigatours in religion, was <hi>cited by me,</hi> you think <hi>in an unhappy hour, becaus,</hi> ſay you, <hi>ther is is not any one ſingle text of ſcriptur more fatal
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57490:17"/>to papal pretenſions.</hi> And why ſo Sir? <hi>becaus</hi> the Goſpel you ſay, <hi>came to Rome</hi> as well as it came to us here in <hi>England.</hi> To this Sir I have already told you, that it came not to us as it came to <hi>Rome:</hi> and now I tell you again, that it came to us from <hi>Rome,</hi> and not to <hi>Rome</hi> from us. And therfor is that text fatal to us, not to them: It may open their mouths, but I am ſure it ſtops ours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heats and reſolutions,</hi> the ſubject of my fourth paragraff, which your ſelf will not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, you will not permit me to diſlike. You may talk againſt them, but I may not. But I may be excuſed; for I knew not then, ſuch a man of art as your ſelf, would ſpeak of that he underſtood better then I do.</p>
               <p>The <hi>motives of moderation</hi> in my ſixt para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graff you laugh at; and I will not ſtop your merriment. But in all this ſay you <hi>Fiat lux hath a ſecret deſign,</hi> which your eagle-ſighted eye has diſcovered. And <hi>in vain is the net ſpread before the eyes of a thing that hath a wing.</hi> And I muſt know, that the authour of <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions,</hi> is that thing that hath a wing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>6</hi> ch. from page 1<hi>48</hi> to <hi>177.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your ſixt chapter, which meets juſt with my ſixt paragraff of the <hi>obſcurity of God,</hi> in the beginning, where you declare the ſufficient knowledg we have of God by divine revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereunto by our humble beleef we have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57490:18"/>ſubſcribed our conſent, is right and good; but not at all againſt me, who there treat a caſe of metaphyſical concernment, which you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend not. It is no wonder then, you ſhould ſo much diſlike all that my plea of uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not only before any teacher appear, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter too; whiles you take the teacher and his words as they walk hand in hand actually linkt together with our beleef in him; which actual beleef my ſuppoſition ſuſpends and ſeparates, to the end I may conſider whether any ſuch teacher can appear ſo accompliſht as to move us, who live in this preſent age, and coin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion anew, to a beleef invariable: ſo that through your too much haſte you utterly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake all my whole diſcours, and ſpeak nothing at all to the caſe I treat of. I ſpeak wholly there, as in other parts of <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> upon a ſuppoſition of the condition, the generality of people are now actually in, here in <hi>England,</hi> where every one lets himſelf looſe at pleaſure to frame opinions and religions of themſelvs. And ſo cannot be thought to ſpeak of a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled beleef, but only of ſettling one, or one to be ſettled; which there and elswhere in that book, I indeavour to ſhow impoſſible to be ſo fixedly ſtated by any private man, but that himſelf and others may rationally doubt it. And that therfor our only way is to beleev and not diſpute, to ſubmit to the old way we have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57490:18"/>formerly received, and not to ſurmiſe a new. This is the very ſubſtance ſcope and purpos not only of that paragraff, but of my whole book, which you do as utterly ſwerv from, as ever any blinded man, put to thraſh a cock, miſplaced his blow. Perhaps it is hard for you to conceiv your ſelf in a ſtate you are not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in at preſent: and if you cannot do this, you will be abſolutely unfit to deal with ſuch hypothetick diſcourſes, as I ſee indeed you are. <hi>Bellarmins</hi> little <hi>catechiſe</hi> had been a fitter book for you to write <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon, than my <hi>Fiat lux.</hi> There is good poſitive do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, ſigned <hi>hic &amp; nunc,</hi> and ſpecified to your inclination and capacity, I meddle not with any: I deliver no poſitive doctrin at all; I never deſcend to any particular concluſion or <hi>theſis</hi> of faith; I defend no opinion but only this, <hi>That every opinion is defenſible, and yet none impregnable.</hi> Do you not bluſh ſir, to ſee your own groſs miſtake. God is my witnes, when I finde you, miſled by your own errour, ſo furiouſly to tax me with ignorance, fraud, blaſphemy, atheiſme, I cannot but pitty you. And generally you talk at random, as well in this chapter as others. Let me give ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hint of it in particular.</p>
               <p>Where I in my foreſaid paragraff ſay that <hi>differences of faith in its branches are apt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a ſuſpition in its very root, and conſequently
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57490:19"/>atheiſme.</hi> To this you reply, that <hi>That diſcours of mine is all rotten:</hi> that <hi>Chriſtian religion it ſelf might thus be queſtioned:</hi> that <hi>it is the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the pagan Celſus:</hi> that <hi>ſuch conteſts have ever been;</hi> that <hi>Proteſtants are reſolved:</hi> that <hi>Catholiks turn atheiſts as well as others:</hi> that <hi>our religion is the ſame yeſterday and to day:</hi> that <hi>our evils are from our ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. Doth this talk concern or plead to my aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? I know all this, as well as you; but that it is nothing to the purpos, that I know, and it ſeems you do not. Though all this you ſay be true, yet ſtill it remains notwithſtanding as true and certain as it was before, and that is certain enough, That difference of faith in its bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are apt to inferre a ſuſpicion in its very root, and conſequently atheiſm. You have but beaten the air.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe unto all that diſcours of mine, <hi>If the Papiſt or Roman Catholik, who firſt brought us the news of our Chriſtianity, be now becom ſo odious, then may likewiſe the whole ſtory of our Chriſtianity be at length thought a Romance,</hi> You ſpeak with the like extravagancy, and mind not my hypothetick at all, to ſpeak direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to my inference, as it became a man of art to do. But neglecting my conſequence, which in that diſcours is principally and ſolely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, you ſeem to deny my ſuppoſition, which, if my diſcours had been drawn into a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57490:19"/>ſyllogiſme, would have been the minor part of it; And it conſiſts of two categories; firſt that the <hi>Papiſt is now becom odious:</hi> ſecond, that the <hi>Papiſt delivered us the firſt news of Chriſtianity.</hi> The firſt of theſe you little heed, the ſecond you deny, <hi>That the Papiſt</hi> ſay you, <hi>or Roman catholik ſirſt brought Chriſt and his Chriſtianity into this land is moſt untrue, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> &amp;c. And your reaſon is, becaus if any <hi>Romans</hi> came hither, they were <hi>not Papiſts,</hi> and indeed our <hi>Chriſtianity came from the Eaſt,</hi> namely by <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea,</hi> &amp;c. And this is all you ſay to my hypothetick or conditional ratiocination; as if I had ſaid nothing at all but that one abſolute category, which being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered before, I now onely ſuppoſe. You uſe to call me a civil logician, but I fear a natural one as you are, will hardly be able to juſtify this motion of yours as artificial. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional hath a verity of its own, ſo far differing from the ſuppoſed category, that this being fals that may yet be true. For example, if I ſhould ſay thus: A man who hath wings as an eagle, or if a man had wings as an eagle, he might fly in the air, as well as another bird. And ſuch an aſſertion is not to be confuted by proving that a man hath not the wings of an eagle. Yet ſo you deal with me here, a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of arts with a civil logician. But, that I may go along with you, we had not ſir our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57490:20"/>immediately from the Eaſt, nor from <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea,</hi> as I have already told you, we Engliſhmen had not. For as he delivered his Chriſtianity to ſom Brittons, when our land was not called <hi>England</hi> but <hi>Albion</hi> or <hi>Brittany,</hi> and the inhabitants were not Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen but Brittons or Kimbrians, ſo likewiſe did that Chriſtianity and the whole news of it quite vaniſh, being ſodainly overwhelmed by the ancient deluge of paganiſme: nor did it ever come from them to us. Nay the Brittons themſelves had ſo forgot and loſt it, that even they alſo needed a ſecond converſion, which they received from Pope <hi>Eleutherius.</hi> And that was the only news of Chriſtianity which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed and laſted even amongſt the very Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons: which ſeems to me a great ſecret of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence in planting and governing his Church; as if he would have nothing to ſtand firm and laſting but what was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately fixed by and ſeated upon that rock. For all other converſions have vaniſht, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeats of the other Apoſtles failed, that all might the better cement in an unity of one head. Nay the tables which God wrote with his own hand were broken, but the other writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Moſes</hi> remained, that we might learn to give a due reſpect to him whom God hath ſet over us as our head and ruler under him, and none exalt himſelf againſt him. I know you
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57490:20"/>will laugh at this my obſervation, but I cannot but tell you what I think. To return then to my former diſcours; when I ſpeak good ſir, of the news of Chriſtianity firſt brought to this land, I mean not that which was firſt brought upon the earth or ſoil of this land, and ſpoken to any body then dwelling here, but which was delivered to the forefathers of the now preſent inhabitants, who be Saxes or Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen. And I ſay that we, the now preſent inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> off-ſpring of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh or Saxons, had the firſt news of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity immediately from <hi>Rome,</hi> and from Pope <hi>Gregorius</hi> the Roman Patriarch, by the hands of his miſſioner Saint <hi>Auſtin.</hi> And this all men know to be as true, as they know, that Papiſts are now becom odious. Sith then the categorick aſſertions are both clear; namely that the Papiſt firſt brought us the news of Chriſtianity, and ſecondly, that the Papiſt is now become odious amongſt us; what ſay you to my conſequence? that the whole ſtory of Chriſtianity may as well be deemed a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, as any part of that Chriſtianity we at firſt received, is now judged to be part of a Romance. This conſequence of mine it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved a man of thoſe great parts you would be thought to have, to heed attentively, and yet you never mind it.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57490:21"/>
               <p>You adde in the cloſe of your diſcours, that <hi>many things delivered us at firſt with the firſt news of Chriſtianity may be afterwards rejected for the love of Chriſt and by the commiſſion of Chriſt?</hi> But ſir, what love of Chriſt dictates, what commiſſion of Chriſt allows you, to choos and reject at your own pleaſure? what heretick was ever ſo much a fool, as not to pretend the love of Chriſt and commiſſion of Chriſt for what he did? How ſhall any one know you do it, out of any ſuch either love or commiſſion? ſith thoſe who delivered the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith now rejected, pretended equal love of Chriſt and commiſſion of Chriſt, for the delivery of them, as of any other. And why may we not at length reject all the reſt, for love of ſomthing els? when this love of Chriſt, which is now crept out into the very outſide of our lips, is ſlipt off thence. Do you think men cannot finde a cavil againſt him, as well as his law delivered unto us with the firſt news of him? and as eaſily dig up the root, as cut up the branches. Is not the thing already don, and many becom atheiſts upon that account. Pray ſpeak to me ſomthing of reaſon. Did not the Jews by pretens of their love to that immortal God, whom their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers ſerved, reject the whole goſpel at once? and why may not we poſſibly as well do it by peece meals! Let us leav cavils: Grant my
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57490:21"/>ſuppoſition which you know you cannot deny: then ſpeak to my conſequence which I deem moſt ſtrong and good, to infer a concluſion which neither you nor I can grant. I tell you plainly and without tergiverſation, before God and all his holy angels, what I ſhould think if I deſcended unto any concluſion in this affair. And it is this: either the Papiſt, who holds at this day all thoſe articles of faith which were delivered at the firſt converſion of this land by S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> is unjuſtly becom odious amongſt us; or els my honeſt Parſons throw off your caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocks, and reſign your benefices and glebe-lands into the hands of your neighbours, whoſe they were aforetime: my conſequence is irrefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable.</p>
               <p>If any part, much more if many parts, great ſubſtantial parts of religion brought into the land with the firſt news of Chriſtianity, be once rejected (as they are now amongſt us) as Romiſh or Romancical, and that rejection or reformation be permitted, then may other parts and all parts, if the gap be not ſtopt, be lookt upon at length as points of no better a condition. Nay it muſt needs be ſo: for the ſame way and means that lopt off ſom bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches will do the like to others, and root too; A villification of that Church, wherein they find themſelvs who have a minde to prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, upon pretens of Scriptur and power of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57490:22"/>interpreting it, light, ſpirit, or reaſon, adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a perſonal obſtinacy that will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, will do it roundly and to effect. This firſt brought off the Proteſtants from the Roman catholick Church, this lately ſeparated the Presbyterian from the Engliſh Proteſtant Church, the Independent from the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, the Quaker from the other Independents. And this laſt good man heeds nothing of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion but only the moral part, which in deed and truth is but honeſt paganiſme. This ſpeech is worthy of all ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And I could wiſh you would ponder it ſeriouſly. See if the <hi>Quaker</hi> deny not as reſolutely the regenerating power of baptiſm, as you the efficacy of abſolution. See if the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> do not with as much reaſon eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate the prelacy of Proteſtants, as they the Papacy. See if the <hi>Socinian</hi> arguments againſt the Trinity, be not as ſtrong as yours againſt the Euchariſt. See if the <hi>Jew</hi> do not with as much plauſibility deride Chriſt, as you his Church. See if <hi>Porphiry, Julian,</hi> and other ancient pagans do not as ſtrongly confute all Chriſtianity, as we any part of it. He is a fool that having a will and power enough, cannot find out as plauſible a pretence for the pulling down of churches, as we had any for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of monaſteries. Ther be books late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth, and by more then one author,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57490:22"/>which do as powerfully diſſipate the conceit we once had of hell, as any ever did elude Purgatory. Did we not lately find out texts and reaſonings againſt our King and monarchy, as many as we found out long ago againſt Pope and popery? Gods providence and our ſouls immortality if any liſt to deny, he may have more abundant argumentations every where occurring, than any other piece of popery now rejected ever felt. If one text of ſcriptur be by a trope of rhetorick made to ſpeak a ſens, contrary to what was believed in catholick times in any one point, cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other text by ſome ſuch ſlight be forced to fruſtrate another. And thus when all articles are at laſt by ſuch tricks of wit caſhiered, can ther be wanting ſeveral appearing incongrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, contradictions, tautologies, improbabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to diſable all holy writ at once. And can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the Jew afford us at laſt arguments enough, to diſſipate at length the very name of Chriſt out of the world, which after the whole ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of his law will but float on mens lips like an empty ſhadow, till it quite vaniſh. Theſe things fir, are not only true, but clear and evident. And nothing is wanting to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify them, but a ſerious conſideration.</p>
               <p>Theſe few words ſir, which I have beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon you by way of ſupererogation, above what I needed, will ſomwhat enlighten you to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57490:23"/>diſcern the goodneſs and neceſſity of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. <hi>If the Papiſt who firſt brought us th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> news of Chriſtianity be now becom odious, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may all Chriſtianity at length be thought a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance,</hi> &amp;c. Religion like a hous, if a breach he once made and not repaired to former unity will by degrees all moulder away, till no one room be left intire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>7</hi> ch. from page <hi>177.</hi> to <hi>188.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your ſeventh chapter finiſhed in five leafs runs, of flies over, no leſs than four of my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraffs at once, which make up above fifty pages, concerning the obſcurity of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Providence.</hi> All which diſcours of mine is, you ſay, <hi>nothing to my purpoſe,</hi> but foiſted in for <hi>a blinde to entertain my readers.</hi> But ſir, thoſe judicious readers you lately left behind you, that diſcern my purpos better than I ſee you do, will tell you, that it is ſo much to my purpos, that nothing could be more. At leaſt you let all paſs without either cenſure or commendation, till you meet happily at length with a word or too of mine (let fall in my ninth paragraff called <hi>Help</hi>) about <hi>ſcripture.</hi> This makes your heart leap; it is a common place you know how to ſport in, and you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meet with that ſound, but it makes you dance. Your chapter then, which is written againſt all my philoſophical diſcours of <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>providence,</hi> is called <hi>ſcripture vindicated,</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57490:23"/>as though I had induſtriouſly wrote againſt ſcripture. And therin you ſweetly dilate upon the excellency and goodneſs of the word of God, as if I had any way diminiſhed it, or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively wrote againſt it; juſt according to the tone of our late diſmal times. <hi>Lord, I am for thy caus Lord, I am left alone to plead thy caus Lord againſt thine enemies.</hi> But ſir, the few words I there ſpeak, only incidentally, in the end of that my paxagraff called <hi>Help,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſurmiſes that men may have about ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as they be but a ſmall part of the many, which I know to be now vented up and down the land in this our preſent ſtate of ſeparation one from another; ſo if I had not given ſom touch of them in that metaphyſick abſtracted diſcours of <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> which proceeds, as I have ſaid, upon a ſuppoſition of our chooſing and making religions here in <hi>England</hi> at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur, unto endles differences and diviſions, it had been a maimed and imperfect work, and no wayes ſatisfactory unto thoſe judicious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders unto whom I write, though you do not. And I cannot but tell you, whatſoever you think of your ſelf, you are in truth but a weak man, except you diſſemble and miſtake on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, to take that as ſpoken abſolutely by me, and by way of poſitive doctrin, which I only deliver upon an <hi>hypotheſis</hi> apparent to all the world beſides your ſelf. I ſpeak upon a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57490:24"/>of doubting, which theſe times have brought upon us, of interpreting, accepting, rejecting, framing, forging religions and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to our ſelves; and you reply againſt me words and diſcourſes that preſuppoſe an aſſent of beleeving. If a man beleev, he cannot doubt. And if he doubt not of the ſcriptures truth, he cannot make exceptions againſt any of its properties. But if any begin to queſtions this, or that, or other part of doctrin contained in ſcriptur, and delivered by thoſe who firſt brought it, as every one does who ſwerves from the Church he found himſelf in, then I ſuppoſe ſuch a one doubts. And being now thereby ſeparated from that body of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers to which he before by faith adhered, he cannot now left to himſelf, but proceed, if he give attendance to the conduct of his own ſurmiſing thoughts, to more ſuſpicions than I was willing to expreſs.</p>
               <p>But ſir, what you ſay here, and ſo often up and down your book, of Papiſts contempt of ſcriptur, I beſeech you will pleaſe to abſtain from it for the time to com: I have converſed with the Roman catholiks of <hi>France, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> I have read more of their books, both hiſtories, contemplatives, and ſchola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick divines, than I beleev you have ever ſeen or heard of. I have ſeen the devotion both of common people, colledges of ſacred prieſts,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57490:24"/>and religious houſes, I have communed with all ſorts of people, and peruſed their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. And after all this, I tell you, and out of my love I tell you, that their reſpect to ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is real, abſolute and cordial even to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration. Others may talk of it, but they act it, and would be ready to ſtone that man that ſhould diminiſh holy writ. Let us not wrong the innocent. The ſcriptur is theirs, and Jeſus Chriſt is theirs, who alſo will plead their caus when he ſees time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>8</hi> ch. from page <hi>188</hi> to <hi>198.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your eight chapter, which falls upon my paragraff of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> you are abſolutely in a wood, and wonder more then ordinary, how that diſcours of mine, concerning reaſon to be excluded from the imploiment of framing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of religion, can any wayes <hi>concern Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> or be a confutation of <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> As though <hi>Fiat lux</hi> were written to any ſuch concernment againſt Proteſtants. Your head is ſo full, it ſeems of that controverting facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for <hi>Proteſtants</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that if <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> be but mentioned in a book without an epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet of deteſtation, you conclude preſently, that the book is written againſt Proteſtants. And if every thing therin contained, anſwer not the idea of your brain, then it is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent with you, it is ſilly, it is beſides the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos. And this cenſur you have given, ſtill as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57490:25"/>you have gone along all my whole book hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, of every part and parcel of it, even from my preface to this preſent paragraff of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> You cannot ſee how all that vain flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing diſcours of mine, concerning diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of feuds, ground of quarrels, nullity of title, heats and reſolution, motives to moderation, obſcurity of God, natur and providence, or the like, ſhould <hi>confute Proteſtancy,</hi> or any way concern Proteſtants. And therfor it is wholly impertinent. Thus the famous Knight, when he had once conceived an idea of his own errantry, every flock of ſheep muſt be an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and every wind-mill a giant, or els it is impertinent to <hi>Don Quixot.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>9</hi> ch. from page <hi>198</hi> to <hi>213.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your ninth chapter upon my paragraff of <hi>Light and Spirit;</hi> is wholly ſpent, neglecting all my other diſcours, in ſolving <hi>the Jewiſh ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> which I anſwer my ſelf. And if you have added any thing better than mine, I ſhall be thankful for it as ſoon as I ſee it. But I fear your vaunting flouriſhes about ſcriptur which you love to talk on, will not without the help of your <hi>credo</hi> and humble reſignation, ſolve the argument; which that you may the eaſlier be quit of, you never examin; but only run on in your uſual flouriſhes about the <hi>uſe and excellency</hi> of <hi>Gods word.</hi> I told you in <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> what the Jew will reply to all ſuch reaſonings,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57490:25"/>but you have the pregnant wit not to heed any thing that may hinder your flouriſhes. But ſir, if you were kept up in a chamber with a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Jew, without bread water and fire, till you had ſatisfied him in that objection; I am ſtill well enough aſſured, for all your aery vaunts, that if you do not make uſe of your <hi>Credo,</hi> which here you contemn, you might there ſtay till hunger and cold had made an end of you. But I beleev you love not ſuch dry blows; however you may be delighted with pen en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters at a diſtance, where after your <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum</hi> has been well inſpired with the warm ſpirits blown hither out of the fortunate iſlands, you may cavil revile and threaten at your pleaſure, and knock down the ſhadow of your adverſary which your own ſpirits have raiſed up, and preſented to you in your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>10</hi> ch. from page <hi>213</hi> to <hi>228.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your tenth chapter runs over two of my paragraffs, which ſpeak the plea of <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> That you eſteem idle, the other ſenſles, the laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient. And to make this laſt good, you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to diſable both what I have ſet down to make againſt the prelate Proteſtant, and alſo what I have ſaid for him. I ſaid in <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> that it made not a little againſt our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, that after the prelate Proteſtancy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57490:26"/>was ſettled in <hi>England,</hi> they were forced for their own preſervation againſt Puritans, to take up ſom of thoſe principles again, which former Proteſtants had caſt down for Popiſh, as is the <hi>autority</hi> of a viſible Church, efficacy of <hi>ordination,</hi> difference between <hi>clergy</hi> and <hi>laiety,</hi> &amp;c. Here firſt you deny <hi>that thoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are popiſh.</hi> But ſir, ther be ſom Jews even at this day, who will deny any ſuch man as <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> to have ever been in <hi>Jury.</hi> I have other things to do, than to fill volums with uſeles texts, which here I might eaſily do, out of the books both of the firſt reformers, and catholik divines and councels. Then ſecondly you challenge me to prove, <hi>that thoſe principles were ever denied by our prelate Proteſtants.</hi> And this you do wittily and like your ſelf. You therfor bid me prove that thoſe principles were ever denied by our prelate Proteſtants, becaus I ſay, that our prelate Proteſtants here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as ſoon as they became ſuch, took up again thoſe forenamed principles, which Proteſtants their forefathers both here in <hi>England</hi> and beyond the ſeas, before our prelacy was ſet up, had ſtill rejected. When I ſay then, that our prelate Proteſtant affirmed and aſſerted thoſe principles which former Proteſtants de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; you bid me prove that our prelate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ever denied them.</p>
               <p>Thus you contradict what I ſay is pleaded
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57490:26"/>againſt our prelate Proteſtant. And again you do as ſtiffly gain-ſay what I plead for him my ſelf. You laugh at me even with head and ſhoulders, and tell me, that the prelate-Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant has far better arguments for themſelvs, than either mine is, or any I can bring; nor do they need the help of ſuch a weak logician as my ſelf, in this their caus. Sir give me leav to tell you here once for all, that I thought it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for my deſign, to ſet down either for Papiſt or Proteſtant, when occaſion required, ſuch reaſons as appeared plauſible to my ſelf; and to ſay all for them that can be ſaid, was neither the work of my ſmall ability, nor any purpoſe of my deſign. And it is enough to me, that I know no better. But let us ſee what my argument is, and how you cruſh it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church,</hi> ſay I, <hi>muſt have a byſhop, or otherwiſe ſhe will not have ſuch a viſible head, as ſhe had at firſt,</hi> &amp;c. This that you may evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, you tell me, that <hi>the Church hath ſtill the ſame head ſhe had, which is Chriſt, who is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with his Church by his Spirit and laws, and is man God ſtill as much as ever he was, and ever the ſame will be: and if I would have any other viſible byſhop to be that head, then it ſeems I would not have the ſame head, and ſo would have the ſame and yet not the ſame.</hi> Thus you ſpeak.</p>
               <p>But ſir, I cannot in any reaſon be thought to ſpeak otherwiſe, if we would uſe true Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57490:27"/>of the identity of the head, than I do of the identity of the body of the Church. This body is not numerically the ſame: for the men of the firſt age are long ago gone out of the world, and another generation com, who yet are a body of Chriſtians of the ſame kind; becaus they adhere to the ſame principles of faith. And as the body is of the ſame kinde, though not numerically the ſame; ſo do I require, that ſince Jeſus Chriſt as man, the head immediate of other beleeving men, is departed hence to the glory of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the Church ſhould ſtill have a head of the ſame kind, as viſibly now preſent, as ſhe had in the beginning; or els ſay I, ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be completely the ſame body, or a body of the ſame kind, completely viſible as ſhe was. But this ſhe hath not, this ſhe is not, except ſhe have a viſible byſhop, as ſhe had in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, preſent with her, guiding and ruling under God. Chriſt our Lord is indeed ſtill man-God, but his man-hood is now ſeparate; nor is he viſibly now preſent as man, which immediately headed his beleevers under God, on whoſe influence that natur depended. His God-head is ſtill the ſame in all things, not only in it ſelf, but in order alſo to his Church, as it was before, equally inviſible, and in the like manner beleeved; but the natur delegate under God, and once ruling viſibly amongſt us
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57490:27"/>by words and examples, is now utterly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn. And if a natur of the ſame kind, be not now delegate with a power of exteriour government, as at the firſt ther was, then hath not the Church the ſame head now, which ſhe had then. <hi>Qui habet aures audiendi audiat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here by the way we may take notice what a ſincere Engliſh Proteſtant you are, who labor ſo ſtoutly to evacuate my argument for epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and leav none of your own behind you, nor acquaint the world with any, although you know far better; but would make us beleev notwithſtanding thoſe far better reaſons for prelacy, that Chriſt himſelf, as he is the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and only head of inviſible influence, ſo is he likewiſe the only and immediate head of viſible direction and government among us, without the interpoſition of any perſon dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate in his ſtead, to overſee and rule under him in his Church on earth: which is againſt the tenour both of ſacred goſpel, and S. <hi>Pauls</hi> epiſtles, and all antiquity, and the preſent eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick polity of <hi>England;</hi> and is the doctrin not of any Engliſh Proteſtant, but of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, Independent and Quaker.</p>
               <p>Chriſt then in your way is immediate head not only of ſubminiſtration and influence, but of exterior derivation alſo and government to his Church. Pray tell me, is he ſuch an immediate head to all beleevers, or no? if he be to all,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57490:28"/>then is no man to be governed in affairs of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by any other man: on the other ſide, if he be not immediate head to all, but mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters head the people, and Chriſt heads the miniſters, this in effect is nothing els, but to make every miniſter a byſhop. Why do you not plainly ſay, what it is more than manifeſt you would have. All this while you heed no more the laws of the land, than conſtitutions of goſpel.</p>
               <p>As for goſpel; That Lord, who had been viſible governour and paſtour of his flock on earth, when he was now to depart hence, as all the apoſtles expected one to be choſen to ſucceed him in his care, ſo did he, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his own inviſible preſence and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence over his flock, publikly appoint one. And when he taught them, that he who were greateſt among them ſhould be as the leaſt, he did not deny but ſuppoſe one greater, and taught in one and the ſame breath, both that he was over them and for what he was over them, namely to feed not to tyranniſe, not to domineer abuſe and hurt, but to direct com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conduct his flock, in all humility and tendernes, as the ſervant of all their ſpiritual neceſſities. And if a byſhop be otherwiſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, it is the fault of his perſon, not his place.</p>
               <p>As for the laws of the land, it is there moſt ſtrongly decreed by the conſent and autority
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57490:28"/>of the whole kingdom, not only that byſhops are over miniſters, but that the kings majeſty is head of byſhops alſo in the line of hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, from whoſe hand they receiv both their place and juriſdiction. This was eſtabliſht not only by one, but ſeveral Parliament acts, both in the reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> and Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.</hi> So that by the laws of the land ther be two greeces between miniſters and Chriſt, which you cut off, to the end you may ſecretly uſurp the autority and place of both, to the overthrow at once both of goſpel and our law too.</p>
               <p>By the laws of our land our ſeries of eccleſiaſtical government ſtands thus,
<list>
                     <item>God</item>
                     <item>Chriſt</item>
                     <item>King</item>
                     <item>Byſhop</item>
                     <item>Miniſters</item>
                     <item>People</item>
                  </list>
the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament is this,
<list>
                     <item>God</item>
                     <item>Chriſt</item>
                     <item>Miniſter</item>
                     <item>People.</item>
                  </list>
So that the miniſters head in the Presbyterian predicament, touches Chriſts feet immediately, and nothing intervenes. You pretend indeed, that hereby you do exalt Chriſt; but this is a meer cheat, as all men may ſee with their eyes; for Chriſt is but where he was; but the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter indeed is exalted, being now ſet in the Kings place, one degree higher then the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, who by law is under both king and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops too</p>
               <p>You will here ſay to me, <hi>What is the Papiſts line of Church government. There the Pope muſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57490:29"/>ſit next Chriſt, and Kings under his feet.</hi> Sir, I have not time in this ſhort letter to diſcours this ſubject, as it deſerves. Nor does it now concern me, who have no more here to ſay than only this; that my argument for prelacy, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in your words you may diſable it, is not weakened by you in deeds at all, and as far as I can perceiv, not underſtood. Yet two things I ſhall tell you over and above what I need in this affair alſo.</p>
               <p>Firſt is, that Roman catholiks do more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cordially acknowledg the reſpective Chriſtian king of any kingdom to be ſupream head of his catholik ſubjects even in affairs of religion, than any other, whether Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Presbyterians, or even prelate Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants have, if we ſpeak of truth and reality, ever done. And this I could eaſily make good both by the laws and practiſes of all catholik kingdoms upon earth in any age on one ſide, and the oppoſite practiſes of all Proteſtants on the other. Second is, that for what reaſon Roman catholiks deny a prince to be head of the Church, for the ſame ought all others as they deny it in deeds, ſo, if they would ſpeak ſincerely as they think and act, to deny it in words alſo, as well as they. For catholiks do beleev him to be head of the Church, from whom the channel of religion and all dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in it is derived and flows; for which
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57490:29"/>reaſon a ſpring is ſaid to be head of a river. But neither does any King upon earth, except he be prieſt and prophet too, ever trouble himſelf to derive religion, as the Pope has ever don: neither does either Proteſtant, Presbyterian or Independent, either in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or elswhere, ever ſeek for religion from the hands of the King, or ſupplicate unto him when any doubt ariſes in thoſe affairs, as they ought in conſcience and honeſty to do, for a final deciſion, any more than the Roman ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik does. So that whatever any of them may ſay, all Proteſtants do as much deny the thing in their behaviour as catholiks do in words; and catholiks do in their behaviour ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv as much, as Proteſtants either practiſe or pretend. What is the reaſon that Roman ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks in all occurring difficulties of faith, both have their recours unto their papal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour (unto whom kings themſelvs for their own eaſe remit them) and acquieſce alſo to his deciſion and judgment, but only becaus they beleev him to be head of the Church. And if Proteſtants have no ſuch recours, nor will not acquieſce to his majeſties authority in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of religion, but proceed to wars and quarrels without end, the prince neglected as wholly unconcerned in thoſe reſolvs, they do as manifeſtly deny his headſhip, as if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt none. Nay to acknowledg a headſhip in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57490:30"/>words and deny it in deeds is but mockery. By theſe two words Sir, it may appear, that the kings majeſty is as much head of the Church to Roman catholiks as to any Proteſtants; and theſe no more than they either derive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or deciſion of their doubts from the kings chair.</p>
               <p>Ith interim it is a ſhame and general ſcandal to the whole world, that we in <hi>England</hi> ſhould neither ſupplicate nor acquieſce in affairs of religion to his judgment, whom in words we acknowledg head of the Church, but fight and quarrel without end; and yet have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to upbraid Roman catholiks with a contrary beleef, who although they ever look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon their papal patriarch as ſpiritual head and paſtour and deriver of their faith, unto whom they ſo ſubmit, that he who after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion remains contumacious forfeits his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, yet have they notwithſtanding in all ages and kingdoms reſigned with a moſt ready cordial reverence unto all deciſions orders and acts of their temporal princes, even in ſpiritual and eccleſiaſtical affairs, as well as civil, ſo far as their laws reached, as ſupreme head and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of their reſpective kingdoms. And all kings and princes find in a very ſhort ſpace, however others may utter hypocritical words of flattery, that indeed none but catholik ſubjects do heed and fear and obſerv them uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:57490:30"/>in all whatever their commands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taught by their religion, of which they alone give account at times appointed for pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to hearken and obey for conſcience ſake all higher powers, conſtituted over them for good.</p>
               <p>That catholiks do univerſally obſerv their king in all affairs as well eccleſiaſtick as civil, I need not, to make it good, ſend you Sir either to the teſtimonies of civil law and <hi>Codex</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian,</hi> or to the other various conſtitutions of ſo many ſeveral provinces and kingdoms, as are and have been in Chriſtendom; our own home will ſuffice to juſtify it. Were not the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al courts, both court Chriſtian, Prerogative court and Chancery, all ſet up in catholik times, about matters of religion and affairs of conſcience, and all mannaged by clerks or clergy men under the king? In brief, where ever any civil coaction or coactive power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervenes, be it in what affair it will, all ſuch power and action who ever uſes it, hath it au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritatively only from the king. For neither Pope, nor Byſhop, nor any Prieſt ought to be a ſtriker, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches: nor have they any lands, or livings, or court, or power to compel or puniſh either in goods or body, but what is lent or given by princes and princely men, out of their love and reſpect to Jeſus Chriſt and his holy goſpel, whoſe news they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57490:31"/>firſt conveighed about the world; although a juſt donation is, I ſhould think, as good a title, as either emption, inheritance, or conqueſt, if it be irrevocable. The king is the only ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker in the land <hi>ex jure,</hi> and the ſword of the almighty is only in his hand; and none can compel or puniſh either in body or goods, but only himſelf, or others by his commiſſion, in any whatever affair. He can either by his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority and laws blunt the ſword of thoſe who have one in their hand, whether by pact or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as have maſters over ſervants and parents over children; or put a civil power into the hands of thoſe who otherwiſe have none, as prelates, prieſts and byſhops. So that although the Pope derive religion, and chiefly direct in it, yet is the king the only head of all civil coercition, as well in Church affairs as any other, which his commands and laws do reach unto.</p>
               <p>So that the line of Church government amongſt Catholiks, ſince the converſion of kings, runs in two ſtreams; the one is of dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the other of coercition, That of dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is from Chriſt to the chief paſtour, from him to patriarchs, then to metropolitans, arch-byſhops, byſhops, prieſts and people: and in this line is no corporal coaction at all, except it be borrowed; nor any other power to puniſh, but only by debarring men from ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57490:31"/>In the other line of corporal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and autority the King is immediately under God the Almighty, from whom he receivs the ſword to keep and defend the dictates of truth and juſtice, as ſupreme governour, tho him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for direction and faith be ſubject to the Church from whoſe hands he received it, as well as other people his ſubjects; after the king ſucceed his princes and governours in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, with that portion of power all of them which they have from him their liege ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign received. This in brief of papal Church government, which we in <hi>England</hi> by our canting talk of the Lord Chriſt, to the end we may be all lords and all Chriſts, have utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubverted.</p>
               <p>Indeed in primitive times the channel of religion for three hundred years ran apart, and ſeparate from civil government which in thoſe dayes perſecuted it. And then the line of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian government was unmixt. None but prieſts guided, defended, governed the Church and Chriſtian flock; which they did by the power of their faith, vertue, ſecret ſtrength, and courage in Jeſus their Lord inviſible. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it pleaſed the God of mercies, to move the hearts of emperors and kings of the earth, to ſubmit unto a participation of grace; unto which they were more eaſily inclined by the innocence and ſanctity of Chriſtian faith, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:57490:32"/>in that particular of peaceful obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto kings and rulers, though aliens, and pagans, and perſecutors of religion. And now kings being made Chriſtian were looked upon by their ſubjects with a double reverence, more loved, more feared, more honoured than before. Nor could Chriſtian people now tell, how to expres that ineffable reſpect they bore their kings, now co-heirs of heaven with them, whom before in their very paganiſme they were taught by their prieſts to obſerv as gods upon earth, not for wrath only or fear of puniſhment, but for conſcience alſo and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of hazarding not onely their temporall contents, but their eternal ſalvation alſo, for their reſiſting autority though reſident in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. And kings on the other ſide, who afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by the counſel of worldly ſenators enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed laws, ſuch as they thought fit for preſent policy, and defended them by the ſword of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, wielded under God to the terrour of evil doers and defence of the innocent, began now, as was incumbent on their duty, to uſe that ſword for the protection of Chriſtianity, and faith, and the better way now chalked out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by Chriſtian prieſts, from Jeſus the wiſdom and Son of God. And by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame holy prelates, abbots and other prieſts, who were now admitted with other ſenators into counſel, did they in all places en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57490:32"/>ſpecial and particular laws anſwerable to the general rule of faith, which they found to be more excellent and perfect, than any judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they had by natural reaſon hitherto diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</p>
               <p>Thus poor Chriſtians, who had hitherto but only a head of <hi>derivation,</hi> of counſel and direction, which could but only bid them have patience for Chriſts ſake, and conform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs to his meek paſſion, when they ſuffered from aliens, and when they ſuffered injury from one another, could only debar the evil doer, if he gave not ſatisfaction, from further uſe of ſacraments; thoſe Chriſtians I ſay, who could hitherto have no other comfort or aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in this world under their ſpiritual pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour, than what words of piety could afford, had now by the grace of heaven princely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectours, royal defenders, and head champions under God, to vindicate and make good all Chriſtian rights, diſcipline, and truths now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and eſtabliſhed from faith, as well as other civil rites and cuſtoms dictated afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time from meer reaſon, equally revengers up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all evil doers indifferently, that were found criminal in affairs, as well purely Chriſtian as civil, ſtill uſing the advice and direction of their prelates and Chriſtian peers in the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and eſtabliſhing of all thoſe laws they were now reſolved to maintain. So it was don
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57490:33"/>in <hi>England;</hi> ſo in all places of the Chriſtian world. And then the line of Chriſtian go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ran mixt, which before was ſingle. And Chriſtians now had a <hi>Joſhua</hi> to their <hi>Aaron,</hi> who were only led by <hi>Moyſes</hi> before. And although <hi>Aaron</hi> was head of the Church, yet <hi>Joſhua</hi> was head and leader, prince and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain of all thoſe people who were of that Church. The chief byſhop is an <hi>Aaron,</hi> and every Chriſtian king a <hi>Joſhua.</hi> And as it is a content and ſupport to <hi>Aaron</hi> to have a <hi>Joſhua</hi> with him, to fight Gods battles and keep the people in awe; ſo is it not a little comfort to <hi>Joſhua</hi> to have an <hi>Aaron</hi> by him, with whom he may conſult. And indeed no kingdom can have a perfect accompliſhment without the preſence of theſe two ſwords, civil and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. <hi>Ecce duo gladij hîc! ſatis eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although Chriſtians even at this day, when any hereſy or novelty ariſes, have ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours unto the ſame head of their religion for a deciſion of the doubt, whom they conſulted before (for as the channel of Chriſtianity is and muſt be ſtill the ſame, ſo muſt the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head be the ſame alſo) yet when the thing is once decided, they have none but kings and governours under him, to ſee the direction ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, as the only overſeers with coactive power to do it.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſee in brief how the Pope is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57490:33"/>head of the Church, and the King head like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and both immediately under God; but with this difference, that the king only go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns Chriſtianity eſtabliſhed in his own roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty by law; the Pope without further law rules and guides all the ſtreams and rivulets of religion, where ever it flows. He is head of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary direction; the king of ſovereign execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: he of guidance and ſpiritual autority only; the king of civil and natural power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in his place and dignity from God above, to maintain any laws as well purely Chriſtian as civil, which himſelf ſhall accept eſtabliſh and promulgate. The Pope perſwades; but the King commands: and although the Pope ſhould formally command, yet vertually and in effect ſuch a command amounts only to a perſwaſion; and he that obeyes not, feels no ſmart for it, except the king be pleaſed to eſpous his caus, and puniſh the contumacious; which if he juſtly do, then have kings a juſt autority in thoſe affairs; if otherwiſe, then hath the Pope no means of help or defence in this world, any more after the converſion of kings than before it; and help himſelf he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not any other way, than only by putting peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of his communion, who care not of it. The Pope is obeyed for conſcience and love only to his religion; the King for wrath and conſcience too: the Pope delivers the rule
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57490:34"/>but in general only, and blunt on one ſide; the king particulariſes and gives it an edg: the Popes headſhip is exerciſed in <hi>Ought and Should be;</hi> the Kings is <hi>Will and ſhall be:</hi> the Pope ſecludes the contumacious from heaven, which he that beleevs not feels not; the King over and above that, cuts off malefactors from the face of the earth too, and they ſhall be made by feeling to beleev it.</p>
               <p>And theſe two defend and ſecure one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and keep both Chriſtians and their faith inviolate. And while Chriſtians themſelvs do both tenderly love their Pape and chief pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour, and ſpring-head of their religion, which is beleeved beyond him to flow inviſibly from God the great ocean of truth; and withall do honor fear, and obſerv their King and princely governour, who only bears the ſword of juſtice and not in vain, to take revenge upon all thoſe, whom the love of religion and ſpiritual ſword of their paſtour will not keep in awe, they do their duty as they ought, and ſhall find happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes therein. I muſt make haſte, and can ſay no more at preſent to this buſines, which as I have told you is ſomwhat beſides my purpos.</p>
               <p>Only one thing I muſt needs tell you before I paſs on. Although a king is in a good and proper ſence ſtiled head as well of Church as State within his own dominions: yet head of the Church <hi>abſolutely,</hi> is ſo proper to the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57490:34"/>Roman Patriarch, that no man upon earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelf hath ever ſo much as pretended to it: and that for ſix reaſons. Firſt becaus <hi>head of the Church abſolutely,</hi> intimates an univerſal right over the guidance of religion, not in one kingdom only but all, where ever that religion is. And the king of <hi>France,</hi> for example, neither did nor can pretend to be head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> much leſs of <hi>Hungary, Spain, Africk, Italy, Greece, Aſia,</hi> &amp;c. Yet ſuch a head there muſt needs be, to the end the Church may be one myſtick and ſpiritual body, at unity in it ſelf. And that head muſt be unlimited to time and place, as the Church it ſelf is ever permanent, and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally ſpread; nor muſt the government alter, as governments of particular kingdoms do. Secondly, head of the Church abſolutely, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves a primacy both of conveighing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting faith: and all princes in Europ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their faith at firſt from prieſts, who ſent for that end from their ſpiritual ſuperior converted their kingdoms, but they never gave faith either to them or their paſtour. Thirdly he that is head of the Church abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, muſt be of the ſame connatural condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the whole hierarchy, to confirm, baptiſe, ordain, preach, attone the almighty by ſacrifice, impoſe hands, ſegregate men from their worldly ſtate unto his own ſpiritual one,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57490:35"/>and in a ſpecial manner to exerciſe thoſe prieſtly functions, unto which he ſegregates them. Fourthly, head of the Church abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to be indifferent unto kingdoms and all ſorts of government, as the religion alſo is, and keep it like it ſelf in all places unaltered in its nature, however in its general dictates it may concur to the direction and good of all people and governments. And therfor he cannot be confined to one place or government, but muſt be as it were ſeparate and in a condition indifferent to all; as a general byſhop, whoſe ſole care is to heed thoſe eradiations of faith ſpread up and down the world, may be and is; when princes heed but their own particular kingdoms, and care not how religion goes in another, any more then their wealth or poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Thus the ſun-beams though they fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral ſoils diverſly affected, yet they keep their own nature unaltered, by vertue of one general fountain-head of light which is indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to every kingdom, and diſpenſes, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and keeps the raies unaltered. Fiftly, the ends and wayes of religion are quite of another nature from all worldly buſineſſes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for require a particular ſuperintendent ſet apart for them; as indeed they ever have had ſince the time of religions firſt maſter, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s he did educate his in order to a life eternal in a government apart, being himſelf a man
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57490:35"/>diſtinct from <hi>Ceſar,</hi> ſo uſed he to ſpeak of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious duties as ſeparate and differing from others; <hi>Reddite</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quae Caeſaris ſunt, Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari, &amp; quae Dei, Deo.</hi> In very truth, the Church and Chriſtianity, as it is a thing acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental to all worldly ſtates, ſo is it ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>induced upon them as an influence of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other rank and order, unto a particular end of future bliſs; whereas all ſtates do of themſelvs aim no further than the peace and happines of this life. And ſo for the particular end and means anſwerable therunto, which religion uſes, it will require a particular and ſpeciall overſeer. Thus <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> though he conceited the celeſtial orbs to be contiguous, and ſo all rapt together in a motion from Eaſt to Weſt, yet becaus they had ſpecial motions of their own, he therfor allowed them particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences to guide thoſe motions. So we ſee in ordinary affairs, a man that hath ſeverall wayes and ends is guided by ſeveral directours, in this by a lawyer, in that by a phyſitian, by a gardener, by a tradeſman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sixtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus head of the Church abſolutely, muſt be one that ſucceds in his chair, whom Jeſus the maſter left and appointed perſonally to feed his flock. No king upon earth ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſit in that Fiſhermans chair, or to ſucceed him in it, which the Pope to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg for ſixteen hundred years hath both chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:57490:36"/>as his right, and actually poſſeſt. And Catholiks are all ſo fixt in this judgment, that they can no more disbeleev it, than they can ceas to beleev in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>11</hi> ch from page <hi>228.</hi> to <hi>246.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your eleventh chapter falls directly upon my fifteenth paragraff of Scriptur. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for I may here expect, you ſhould inſult over me to the purpos. But Sir I told you before, and now tell you again, that I know no other rule to Chriſtians either for faith or manners, no other hope, no other comfort, but what ſcriptur and holy goſpel affords. But this is not any part of the debate now in hand, however you would perſwade the world to think ſo. When four or five men of ſeveral judgements collected from the very ſcriptur you and I talk of, riſe up one againſt another, with one and the ſame ſcriptur in their hands, with ſuch equal pretence of light power and reaſon, that no one will either yield to another, or remain himſelf in the ſame faith, but run endles diviſions without contronl: does ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptur prevent this evil? does it, has it, can it remedy it? can any one man make a religion by the autority of ſcriptur alone, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther himſelf nor any other, upon the ſame grounds he framed it, ſhall rationally doubt of. This is our caſe and only this; which you do not ſo much as take notice of, to the end you
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57490:36"/>may with a more plauſible rhetorick, inſult over me as a contemner of Gods word. Nor do you heed any particle of my diſcours in this paragraff, but according to your manner collect principles to the number of ſeven, out of it, you ſay, which I do not know to be ſo much as hinted in it, that as you did before, ſo you may now again play with your own bauble, and refute your ſelf. And they are in a manner the very ſame you ſported with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in your ſecond chapter. 1 <hi>from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans we received the goſpel.</hi>2 <hi>what is ſpoken in ſcriptur of the Church belongs to the Roman.</hi>3 <hi>the Roman every way the ſame it was,</hi> &amp;c. of all which I do not remember that I have in that my paragraff ſo much as any word. Sir either ſpeak to my diſcours as you finde it, or els hold your peace.</p>
               <p>As if then you had overheard me afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, to give you this deſerved check, at the cloſe of your chapter, you bring in ſom few words of mine, with a ſhort anſwer of your own, annext to the skirts of it; which I here ſet down as you place them your ſelf. No man can ſay, ſpeaks <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> what ill popery ever did in the world, till <hi>Henry</hi> the eights dayes, when it was firſt rejected. <hi>Strange,</hi> ſay you in your Animadverſions, <hi>when it did all the evils that ever were in the Chriſtian world.</hi> With the Roman catholiks unity ever dwelt. <hi>Never</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:57490:37"/>Proteſtants know their neighbour catholiks, not their religion. <hi>They know both.</hi> Proteſtants are beholding to Catholiks, for their benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, books, pulpits, goſpel. <hi>For ſom, not all.</hi> The Pope was once beleeved general paſtour over all. <hi>Prove it.</hi> The ſcriptur and goſpel we had from the Pope. <hi>Not at all.</hi> You cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leev the ſcriptur, but upon the autority of the Church. <hi>We can and do.</hi> You count them who brought the ſcriptur as lyars. <hi>No otherwis.</hi> The goſpel ſeparated from the Church can prove nothing. <hi>Yes it ſelf.</hi> This ſhort work you make with me. And to all that ſerious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours of mine concerning ſcriptur, which takes up ſixteen pages in <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> we have got now in reply thereunto, this your Laconick confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. <hi>Strang. Never. Know both. Som not all. Prove it. Not at all. Can and do. No otherwis. Yes it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>12</hi> ch. from page <hi>246</hi> to <hi>262.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your twelfth chapter meets with my hiſtory of Religion, as a flint with ſteel, only to ſtrike fire. For not heeding my ſtory which is ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous temperate and ſober, you tell another of your own, fraught with defamations and wrath, againſt all ages and people: and yet ſpeak as confidently, as calm truth could do. Firſt you ſay that <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea was in England, but he taught the ſame religion that is in England now.</hi> But what religion is that Sir?
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57490:37"/>Then; you tell us <hi>that the ſtory of Fugatius and Damian miſſioners of Pope Eleutherius you do ſuſpect for many reaſons.</hi> But becaus you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign none, I am therfor moved to think they may be all reduced to one, which is, that you will not acknowledge any good thing, ever to have come from <hi>Rome: Then,</hi> ſay you, <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded times af luxury, ſloth, pride, ambition, ſcandalous riots and corruption both of faith and manners, over all the Chriſtian world, both prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, prieſts, prelates and people.</hi> Not a grain of vertue or any goodnes we muſt think, in ſo many chriſtian kingdoms and ages. <hi>Then did Goths and Vandals and other pagans overflow the Chriſtian world.</hi> Either to puniſh we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leev, or teach them how to mend their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>Theſe pagans took at laſt to chriſtianity.</hi> Haply, becaus it was a more looſe and wicked life, then their own pagan profeſſion. <hi>Theſe men now chriſtened advanced the Popes autority, when Chriſtian religion was now grown degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</hi> And now we come to know, how the Roman byſhop became a patriarch above the reſt, by means namely of new converted pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. It was an odde chance, they ſhould think of advancing him to what they never knew, either himſelf or any other advanced before amongſt Chriſtians, whoſe rotten and corrupt faith they had lately embraced. And yet more odde and ſtrange it was, that all
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57490:38"/>Chriſtendom ſhould calmly ſubmit to a power, ſet up anew by young converted pagans; no prince or byſhop either there or of any other Chriſtian kingdom, either then or ever after to this day excepting againſt it. Had not all the byſhops and prieſts of <hi>Africa, Egypt, Syria, Thrace, Greece,</hi> and all the Chriſtian world acknowledged by a hundred experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the ſupreme ſpiritual autority of the Roman patriarch in all times, before this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Goths and Vandals? But why do I expoſtulate with you, who write theſe things not to judicious readers, but fools and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who are not more apt to tell a truth, than to beleeve a lye. But what follows next. <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the beginning of this lurry,</hi> ſay you, <hi>were the Brittons extirpated by the Saxes, who in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertimes received Auſtin from Rome, a man very little acquainted with the goſpel.</hi> Here's the thanks good S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath, who out of his love and tendernes to our nations welfar, after ſo long and tedious journeyes, entered upon the wild forreſt of our paganiſme, with great hazards and inexpreſſable ſufferings of hunger cold and other corporal inconveniences, to communicate <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> and his life and grace unto our nation. <hi>After this,</hi> ſay you, <hi>religion daily more and more declined till the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation roſe.</hi> This is the ſum of your ſtory; which if I like not, <hi>I may thank my ſelf,</hi> ſay
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:57490:38"/>you, <hi>for putting you in mind of it.</hi> Indeed Sir, it is ſo fals and defamatory, and loaden with foul language, not only againſt all nations, ages and people of all conditions, but againſt the honour of ſacred goſpel it ſelf, which muſt utterly dy and have no life or power in the world for ſo many ages together, that I think neither I, or any els can like it, that bears any reſpect either to modeſty religion or truth. You ſay in this your chapter that <hi>I am better at telling a tale then mannaging an argument:</hi> but I ſhall now beleev, that you are equally good at both.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>13</hi> ch. from page <hi>262</hi> to <hi>278.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your thirteenth chapter takes up my three following paragraffs about the <hi>hiſtory of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> wherein, after that according to your wonted manner you tell me, that I <hi>do not my ſelf underſtand</hi> what this thing, that thing, the other thing means, altho it be part of my own diſcours, you ſay at length, that <hi>ther is no ſuch matter,</hi> as I ſpeak; make another ſtory of your own of the ſame mettle with your former, impoſing afreſh upon popery (by which: I do not indeed know what you mean) a wain-load of adulteries, drunkennes, atheiſm, poiſonings, avarice, pride, cruelties, tumults, blaſphemy, rebellions, wars, crimes, and yet threatning to ſay if you ſhould chance to be provoked, far harder things then theſe. Sir, may no man provoke a waſp.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:57490:39"/>
               <p>But if this be the right character of <hi>popery,</hi> which here and elswher up and down your book you give us, I tell you firſt, it will be a difficult matter to know in what age or place <hi>popery</hi> moſt raigns; ſecondly, that it is a thing I am ſo far from excuſing, that I wiſh it back to the pit of hell from whence it iſſued; thirdly, that Roman catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks, if you be indeed againſt this popery, are all on your ſide; for to my knowledg their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is as oppoſite to it, as light to darknes, or God to Belial; laſtly, that you need not be ſo tenderly fearful for the ſpreading of <hi>popery;</hi> for honeſt men will be ready to ſtone him that teaches it; and knaves, hypocrites, adulterers, traitors, theevs, drunkards, atheiſts; rebels, if you have given a right deſcription of popery, are all Papiſts already; theſe need no converſion, the other will by no rhetorick be moved to it. Indeed you fright us all from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtry. For though ſom love iniquity as it is gainful or pleaſurſom, and muſt needs ſuffer for it when they are condemned at the ſeſſions, and cannot avoid it; yet is no man willing to ſuffer either loſs of goods or impriſonment, death or baniſhment, for the bare name of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, that hath neither gain nor pleaſur in it. In a word, wicked men will act your popery, but not own it. And they which own a pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which I ſee you are not acquainted withal,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:57490:39"/>will not only diſlike others, but hate themſelvs, if through any frailty or paſſion they ſhould ever fall into any article of your <hi>popery</hi> here deſcribed. Good Sir, take heed of blaſpheming that innocent Catholik flock, which the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God watch over to protect them. Be afraid to curs them, whom God hath bleſſed, or impoſe that upon their religion which it deteſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>14</hi> ch. from page <hi>278</hi> to <hi>286.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your fourteenth chapter which is upon my title of <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> you labour to ſhow that the <hi>contradictions,</hi> which I mentioned in <hi>Fiat lux</hi> to be put upon popery, are no <hi>contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> at all. Well Sir, although ſlanders put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them be never ſo contradictory and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, yet muſt they have patience: all is true enough, if it be but bad enough. While our Kings raign in peace, then the Papiſts religion is perſecuted, as contrary to monarchy: when we have deſtroyed that government, then is the papiſt haraſſed, ſpoiled, pillaged, murdered, becauſe their religion is wholly addicted to monarchy, and Papiſts are all for Kings. Have not theſe things been done over and over, within the ſpace of twenty years here lately in <hi>England?</hi> All men now alive have been eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes of it: Theſe things as put upon Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ceas to be contradictions: And if they ſhould be contradictions, both parts are therfor
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57490:40"/>true in our countrey logick, becaus they are put upon Papiſts. Is there not ſomthing of the power of darknes in this?</p>
               <p>One latin word of mine which ſhuts up that my Paragraff of <hi>Diſcovery, Ejice ancillam cum puero ſuo,</hi> becaus I engliſh it not, you tranſlate it for me, or rather interpret it, <hi>Banniſh all men out of England but Papiſts:</hi> this according to your gloſs muſt be my meaning. And you ſeem to exult, that <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> who in outward ſhow pretends ſo much moderation, ſhould let fall a word that betrayes no little miſchief in his heart. Good Lord whither does paſſion hurry mans ſpirit! All that period of mine in the end of the foreſaid § is but meerly coppied out of one of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> letters, which he wrote to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> the fourth chapter of that Epiſtle, wherein thoſe very words, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a paſſage in <hi>Moſes</hi> his Pentateuch, are expreſt. Do you either read in your Engliſh bible, <hi>Banniſh all men out of England?</hi> or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any ſuch meaning of <hi>Ejice ancillam cum puero ſuo,</hi> Gal. 4.30. Pray peruſe the ten laſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that chapter attentively; and ſee if I have not in my diſcours ſo coppied out their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and very words too, ſo far as it behooved; that I have done nothing els. <hi>Abraham had two ſons,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul, one of a handmaid, the other of a free woman,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Theſe things are an allegory,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But as then, he that was born af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57490:40"/>the fleſh perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit, even ſo it is now. But what ſaith the ſcriptur? caſt out the bondwoman with her ſon: for the ſon of the bondwoman ſhall not be heir with the ſon of the freewoman,</hi> &amp;c. Pray tell me ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly; Did the apoſtle mean by thoſe words, <hi>Caſt out the bondwoman with her ſon,</hi> that the ſons of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſhould be put to the ſword or baniſht out of their kingdom? Now pray hear my diſcours which I coppied out of that ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal; <hi>If my reader here be cautious, he may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcern a reaſon, why all theſe ſects are ſo boiſterous one againſt another, and every one of them againſt the Roman catholik. Iſmael di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed the whole hous, and was ever quarrelling and buſtling againſt Iſaac. The reaſon is the ſame both here and there. Iſmael was a natural ſon, and Iſaac the legitimate heir. And natural ſons be generally ſeditious, violent and clamorous. As Iſmael therfor was Iſaac his natural bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo is a proteſtant miniſter but the by-blow of a catholick Prieſt; the Presbyterian like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to him: and ſo forward, till you com to the Quaker, who was begot by a deluſion, and brought into the world by a fright: his hand is againſt every man, and every mans hand againſt him. The remedy and only means of peace is, Ejice ancillam cum puero ſuo.</hi> Theſe be my words out of S. <hi>Paul;</hi> and what is his meaning, the ſame is mine. But you will have me in ſpight
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57490:41"/>of my teeth, becaus I ſpeak nothing but good, ſtill to mean ſom evil. I thought S. <hi>Paul</hi> had meant by thoſe words, if I muſt needs diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my underſtanding to you, that the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Iſaacs</hi> were the only ſons of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed love and favour, the inheritance of which bleſſing boiſterous <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> can never work out to themſelvs, by all their perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and buſtling contentions. And according to this meaning I concluded, that to conſider and think ſeriouſly of this, were the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy and means of peace amongſt us here in <hi>England. Eijce ancillam cum puero ſuo</hi> is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt all contentious emulations, which are a ſuſpicious mark not of an elect but of a reprobate. But I muſt neither think nor ſpeak, nor mean, but what you will have me to do; and that ſhall ſtill be ſomthing that is odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. An emblem hereof was the rod of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which taken in the right end was a walking ſtaff; in the wrong, a ſerpent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>15</hi> ch. from page <hi>286.</hi> to <hi>304.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your fifteench chapter, upon my paragraff of <hi>Meſſach,</hi> you are in a mighty plunge what this <hi>Meſſach</hi> ſhould be, and what the <hi>etimology</hi> of that word. <hi>Latin</hi> it is not, <hi>greek</hi> it is not, and you are ſure it is not <hi>hebrew;</hi> ſurely it is, ſay you, <hi>ſom uncouth word, like that of the Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks Paldabaoth.</hi> Alas good Sir, it is Engliſh, a pure Engliſh word; uſed here in <hi>England</hi> all
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57490:41"/>the Saxons times, and ſom hundred years after the conqueſt, till the French monoſyllable had by little and little worn out the laſt ſyllable of the word. And you may finde it yet in the old Saxon laws which I have read my ſelf, thoſe eſpecially of King <hi>Ina,</hi> if I rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the name, which be yet extant, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſtrict care and proviſion is made that a due reverence be kept by all people in the Church all the time of their <hi>Meſſach,</hi> which now we call <hi>Meſs</hi> or <hi>Maſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then having laughed at my admiration of catholik ſervice, you carp at me for ſaying that the <hi>first Chriſtians were never called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to hear a ſermon;</hi> and to convince me, you bring <hi>ſom places out of S. Pauls Epiſtles, and the Acts, which commend the miniſtery of the word:</hi> This indeed is your uſual way of refuting my ſpeeches; you flouriſh copiouſly in that which is not at all againſt me, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver apply it to my words, leſt it ſhould appear, as it is, impertinent. I deny not that converts were further inſtructed, or that the preaching of Gods word is good and uſeful: but that which I ſay is, that primitive Chriſtians were never called together for that end, as the great work of their Chriſtianity. This I have ſo clearly proved, both in the ſecond dialogue of the <hi>Reclaimed Papiſt,</hi> and alſo in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid paragraff of <hi>Meſſach,</hi> that you divert
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57490:42"/>from that, to declaim of the neceſſity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of preaching, and bring neither text nor reaſon that may reach to my words at all.</p>
               <p>You go on, and wonder much, that <hi>we ſhould hear nothing in ſcriptur of this Chriſtian ſacrifice, if any ſuch were.</hi> Sir, you will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hear nor ſee. But, ſay you, <hi>the paſſion of our Lord is our Chriſtian ſacrifice.</hi> Do not I ſay ſo too? But that this incruent ſacrifice was inſtituted by the ſame Lord before his death, to figur out daily before our eyes that paſſion of his, which was then approaching, in commemoration of his death, ſo long as the world ſhould laſt; this, though I plainly ſpeak it, you take no notice of it. But <hi>the Judaical ſacrifice,</hi> ſay you, <hi>is ſaid by the apoſtle in his epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Hebrews, in this to differ from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Chriſtians, that ours was don but once, theirs often.</hi> It is true the ſacrifice of our Lords paſſion, of which the apoſtle in that whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours intends only to treat, in oppoſition to that of bulls and goats, was ſo don but once, that it could not be don twice. But as the ſacrifices of the old law, were inſtituted by almighty God, to be often iterated before the paſſion of the Meſſias for a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual exerciſe of religion; ſo did the ſame Lord for the very ſame purpos inſtitute another to be iterated after his death, unto which it were to have reference, when it ſhould be paſt, as
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57490:42"/>the former had to the ſame death, when it was to com. And it hath a reference ſo much the more excellent, as that it doth by the almighty power of the ſame Meſſias, exhibit to the eye of his beleevers, that very true real body as crucified amongſt us, wherof the former Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical ſacrifices gave meerly a ſhadow. Did not our Lord do this? were not the apoſtles ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this rite <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing to our great Lord God, when S. <hi>Paul</hi> was by impoſition of hands ſegregated from the laity for his divine ſervice, as I clearly in that my paragraff evince out of the hiſtory of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the apoſtles. <hi>No,</hi> ſay you, <hi>the apoſtles were not then about any ſacrifice, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preaching Gods word, or ſom ſuch thing to the people, in the name and behalf of God.</hi> But Sir, is this to be in earneſt or to jeſt? The ſacred text ſayes, they were ſacrificing to our Lord, liturgying, and miniſtring to him. You ſay they were not ſacrificing to God, but only prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to the people. And now the queſtion is, whether you or I more rightly underſtand that apoſtolical book. For my ſence and meaning I have all antiquity, as well as the plain words of ſacred text, you have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>16</hi> ch. from page <hi>304</hi> to <hi>313.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your ſixteenth chapter upon my paragraff of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which is, you ſay, <hi>the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:57490:43"/>moſt diſingenuous of all my book,</hi> is ſpent in an <hi>invective againſt calumnies,</hi> which brings you upon your often iterated common place of <hi>Pagans reproaches to Chriſtians.</hi> And whatever my paragraff may be, this your chapter ſeems to me as ingenious as the very beſt of your book, and abſolutely frivolous. And muſt you inveigh againſt calumnies, whoſe whole book is nothing els? it is a bundle of ſlanders, and a meer quiver of ſharp arrows of deſolation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>17</hi> ch. from page <hi>313</hi> to <hi>325.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your ſeventeenth chapter upon my paragraff of <hi>Images</hi> or <hi>Figures,</hi> nibbles at more of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours made in that one paragraff, then you have taken notice of in ten of my others. And therfor I mean to com up cloſe to you. <hi>A man,</hi> ſay you, <hi>may indeed have ſuch thoughts of devotion, as Fiat lux ſpeaks of, upon the ſight of images which he ſees hanging in Churches, if he be a man diſtraught of his wits, not if he be himſelf and ſober.</hi> So then, mad men it ſeems can tell what figures repreſent, ſober and wiſe men cannot. Again, <hi>The violation of an image,</hi> ſay you, <hi>redounds to the prototype, if it be rightly and duly repreſented, not els.</hi> And when then is Chriſt crucified, for example, rightly and duly repreſented? Are you one of thoſe can tell what figures repreſent, or not. <hi>The hanging up of traitors in effigie is don</hi> ſay you, <hi>only to make a declaration of the fact, and not to caſt a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57490:43"/>upon the perſon.</hi> So you ſay: Becaus you know it don long after the fact has rung all the whole kingdom over; and don not in places of concours, but ignominy; not in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> but <hi>Tiburn;</hi> not with any characters declaring the fact, but with a halter about his neck, to denote the death and ignominy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, as far as is poſſible, upon him. You go on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where the Pſalmiſt complains of Gods enemies breaking down his ſculptures, he means not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any images or figures, but only wainſcot or carved ceiling.</hi> Surely the Prophet wanted a word then to expreſs himſelf, or tranſlatours to expreſs the Prophet. If we muſt gueſs at his meaning without heeding his words, one might think it as probable, that the hous of God was ordained with ſculptures of <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims,</hi> and other angels, to repreſent his true hous that is above, as with the circles, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drats, triangls, rhombos, and rhomboides of wainſcot. <hi>The eye,</hi> ſay you again, <hi>may not have her ſpecies as well as the ear, becaus God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the one and not the other.</hi> This Sir you only ſay. <hi>Fiat lux</hi> makes it appear, that God commands and commends both, and the nature of man requires both: nor can you give any reaſon, why I may not look upon him who was crucified, as well as hear of him. You adde. <hi>Nor is the ſole end of preaching as Fiat lux would
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:57490:44"/>have it, only to move the mind of the hearers unto correſponding affections.</hi> Why do not you ſay then, what els it is for? you deny my words, but declare your ſelf no other end, but what I have in thoſe ſhort words expreſt. You may haply conceal in your heart ſome other end of your preaching, which you are loath to ſpeak; as to procure applaus, to vent your rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, to get good benefices, to ſhow your fine cloth and ſilks, your pure neat white ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched bands and cuffs, button'd handkerchiefs, and ladies gloves, to inflame factions, get wives, or the like; but I could not think of all things at once; nor needed I to expreſs any more, than that one end of preaching which is connatural, apoſtolical, and legal. You go on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God indeed commanded the Cherubims to be ſet upon the ark, but thoſe cherubims were ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of nothing; of what ſhould they be images. Nor were they ſet up to be adored. Beſides God who commanded them to be ſet up, did no more gain-ſay his own prohibition of images to be made, than he contradicted his own rule which forbids to ſteal, when he commanded his people to ſpoil the Egyptians.</hi> But Sir, ſince the real Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims are not made of our beaten gold; thoſe ſet up by <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt be only figures. And of what els ſhould they be figures but of thoſe real ones. Nor is it either to my purpos or
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57490:44"/>yours, that they are ſet up to be adored. For images in catholick Churches, are not ſet up for any ſuch purpos; nor do I any where ſay it. No man alive has any ſuch thought, no tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, no councel hath delivered it, no pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis infers it. Chriſtian Philoſophers or Schooolmen have indeed raiſed a philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal queſtion; <hi>Whether any reſpect may be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated upon the Figur,</hi> purely as it is ſuch an abſolute entity in it ſelf, beſides that relative one that falls only upon the prototype: But what they queſtion, or what they talk, or what they reſolve, does no more belong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus they ſay it, unto catholik faith, then if they had been aſleep and ſaid nothing. All catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik councels and practis declares ſuch ſacred figurs, to be expedient aſſiſtants to our thoughts in our divine meditation and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and that is all that I know of it. And the relative reſpect that is given to any figur as it is ſuch a figur, whether in a glaſs, or in any more fixed poſtur to ſupply the defects of a mirrour, that it terminates naturally upon the ſampler or prototype is evident to right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and philoſophy. And it cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>That which you ſpeak of the Iſraelites ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Egyptians by Gods command, hath ſom ſpecies of an argument in it. But Sir, we muſt know, you as well as I, that God
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57490:45"/>who forbids men to ſteal, did not then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to ſteal, as you ſay he did, when he bad his people ſpoil the Egyptians under the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of a loan. Many things legitimate that their act of ſpoil, and clear it from any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theft or robbery or ſtealing. Firſt, they might have of themſelvs a right to thoſe few goods, in ſatisfaction of the long oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they had unjuſtly undergon: and it may be that in that their great haſt, their own al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance was not then paid them. But ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becaus it is a thing of danger, that any ſervant ſhould be allowed to right himſelf, by putting his hand to his maſters goods, though his caſe of wrong be never ſo clear, therfor did the command of God intervene to juſtify their action. And the abſolute dominion of the whole earth and all that is in it, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeperably in the hands of God, made that by Gods expreſs command to be truly now and juſtly the Hebrews right, which by an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and ſubordinate title, ſuch as is in the hand of creatures, belonged to the Egyptians before. So that the Hebrews in taking thoſe goods with them, did not ſteal: nor did God command them to ſteal, when he bad them car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thoſe goods of the Egyptians with them; for that upon that very command of God they now ceaſed to be the Egyptians any more. But this can no wayes be applied to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57490:45"/>the buſines of <hi>Images:</hi> nor could God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Hebrews to make any images, if he had abſolutely forbidden to have any at all made. For this concerns not any affair between neighbour and neighbour, wherof the ſupreme Lord hath abſolute dominion, but the ſervice only and adoration due from man to his maker, which God being eſſentially good and immutably true cannot alter or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens with. Nor doth it ſtand with his natur and deity to chang, diſpens, or vary the firſt table of his law concerning himſelf, as he may the ſecond which concerns neighbours; for want of that dominion over himſelf, which he hath over any creature, to give or take away its right, to preſerv or deſtroy it, as himſelf pleaſes. God may diſable my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours right, and inable me to take to my ſelf that which before was his, but he cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me to commit idolatry or diſhonour himſelf. If he ſhould deny himſelf, he would not be God. From hence it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that if it be the ſens and mind of the almighty, that to ſet up any images in Churches be derogatory to his glory, then could not God poſſibly command any to be ther ſet up. For theſe two precepts, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſet up ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhalt ſet up none,</hi> are not only contradictory in terms of the law propoſed, enounced and promulgated, but infer alſo in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57490:46"/>God himſelf that contradiction, oppoſition and ſelf-denial, which is inconſiſting with ſuch an unchangeable veracity. God may poſſibly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me either to curs or ſpoil my neighbour, or in a caſe expreſt not to help him; but he ſhould deny himſelf (which the deity cannot do) if either he ſhould command me to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme himſelf, or the honour due to him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to refuſe it him, or give it to another. When therfor one and the ſame God ſo often forbids his people to make <hi>to themſelvs</hi> any images; and yet in the ſame divine law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to ſet up Cherubims in his own temple; it cannot, being a concernment of his worſhip, be otherwayes meant, than that they ſhould make no ſculptures or figurs, but what himſelf commands, and which may aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly repreſent perſons dear to himſelf, as <hi>Fiat lux</hi> interprets it. And if an image in it ſelf be oppoſite to Gods glory, as Anticatholiks think, then could not God poſſibly command the making or ſetting up of any, in his holy temple or place of divine worſhip. But you go on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fiat lux ſayes, God forbad forreign images, ſuch as Moloch, Dagon, and Aſtaroth, but he commanded his own. But Fiat lux is deceived in this as well as other things, for God forbad any likeneſſes of himſelf; and he gives the reaſon, becaus, ſaith he, in Horeb ye ſaw no ſimilitude of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:57490:46"/>me.</hi> Sir, you may know and conſider, that the ſtatues and graven images of the heathens, towards whoſe land <hi>Iſrael</hi> then in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was journeying, to enter and take poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were ever made by the pagans to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent God, and not any devils, although they were deluded in it. And therfor were they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>gods</hi> of the mountains, the <hi>gods</hi> of the valleys, the <hi>gods</hi> of <hi>Accaron, Moab,</hi> &amp;c. Ther was therfor good reaſon; that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, who ſhould be cautioned from ſuch ſnares, ſhould be forbidden to make to <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs</hi> any ſimilitude or likenes of God. What figur or ſimilitude the true God had allowed his people, that let them hold and uſe, until the fulnes of time ſhould com, when the figur of his ſubſtance, the ſplendour of his glory, and only image of his natur ſhould appear. And now good Sir, ſince God has been pleaſed to ſhow us his face, pray give Chriſtians leav to uſe, and keep, and honour it. If you be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded, and take pleaſur in defacing his figurs, I think they have good reaſon on their ſides, who honour them. You proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a pretty fanſy in Fiat lux, to ſay we have as well a precept, Thou ſhalt make graven ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as we have, Thou ſhalt not. I wonder where Fiat lux finds that precept, ſith all ancients have it, and all tranſlations read it, Thou ſhalt not.</hi> What is that <hi>It</hi> they have, what is that <hi>It</hi> they
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57490:47"/>read. Do you think that <hi>Fiat lux</hi> reads one and the ſame text, both <hi>Thou ſhalt</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhalt not. Moſes</hi> his <hi>making</hi> and the <hi>command given him to make Cherubims,</hi> is a rule good enough to <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> that ſom images may be made and ſet up in Churches: as alſo is that precept. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any images,</hi> another rule to ſhow him, that ſome images we are not to make to our ſelvs on our own heads, in imitation of pagans.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No leſs whimſical is that relation Fiat lux ſayes an image hath to ſom one prototype, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to S. Peter rather then to Simon Magus: for ther can be no relation, but what the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either of the framer of ſpectatour makes.</hi> Sir, ſpeaking as I do of a formal repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or relation, and not of the efficient caus of it, I cannot but wonder at this your illogical aſſertion. Is the pictur made by the ſpectators imagination to repreſent this or that thing? or the imagination rather guided to it by the pictur? By this rule of yours the image of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> did not my imagination help it, would no more repreſent a man than a mous. I know the imagination can, for want of real picturs, make fantaſtical ones to it ſelf; in the clouds, walls, ayr, or fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But when ſhe hath real ones, made her either by art or natur, ſhe cannot make them to be otherways then they are; nor think or ſay, except ſhe will abuſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57490:47"/>her ſelf to deriſion, that a cat is a dog, or an ox a hare. Nor does it help you at all, that ther may be miſtakes; for we treat not here of the errours but natures of things. And you will not, I hope, maintain, that ther is no real heat any where, but what the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation makes, becaus the good poor man of <hi>Norway</hi> ſent out of his own countrey upon an errand, ſtood warming his fingers there, at a hedg of red roſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>18</hi> ch. from page <hi>325</hi> to <hi>365.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your eighteenth chapter, which is upon my paragraff of <hi>Tongues</hi> or <hi>Latin ſervice,</hi> hath ſom colour of plauſibility. But becaus you neither do, nor will underſtand the cuſtoms of that Church, which you are eager to oppoſe; all your words are but wind. I have heard many grave proteſtant divines, ingeniouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, that divine comfort and ſanctity of life requiſite to ſalvation which religion aims at, may with more perfection and leſs incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience be attained by the cuſtoms of the Roman Church, than that of ours. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is not to ſit pierching upon the lips, but to be got by heart, it conſiſts not in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but doing; and in this not in that lives the ſubſtance of it, which is ſoon and eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed. Chriſt our Lord drew a compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of all divine truths into two words, which his great apoſtle again abridged into one.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:57490:48"/>And if the ſeveral goſpels for every day in the year, which are or may be in the hands of all catholiks, the chiefeſt particles of divine epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, books of ſacred hiſtory and meditation upon all the myſteries of ſalvation, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual treatiſes for all occaſions and uſes, which be numberles amongſt catholiks, adjoyned to the many ſeveral rites of examination of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, daily and continual practis of prayer and faſting, and an orderly commemoration of the things God hath wrought for us throughout the year, which all by law are tied to obſerv, and do obſerv them, may not give a ſufficient acquaintance of what concerns our ſalvation, and promote them enough towards it, I am to ſeek what it is that can; or what further good it may do, to read the letter of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> epiſtles, to the <hi>Romans</hi> for example, or <hi>Corinthians,</hi> wherein queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and caſes and theological diſcourſes are treated, that vulgar people can neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, nor are at all concerned to know. And I pray you tell me ingenuouſly, and without heat, what more of good could accrew to any by the tranſlated letter of a book, whereof I will be bold to ſay that nine parts in ten con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern not my particular, either to know or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis; than by the conceived ſubſtance of Gods will to me, and my own duty towards him? or what is ther now here in <hi>England</hi> when the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57490:48"/>letter of ſcriptur is ſet open to every mans eye, any more either of peace or charity, piety or juſtice, than in former catholik times, when the ſubſtance of Gods word and will was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven people in ſhort, and the obſervance of their duty prolixly preſt upon them. What did they do in thoſe ancient catholik times? they flockt every day in the week to their Churches, which ſtood continually open, there to pray and meditate and renew their good purpoſes; they ſung pſalms, hymns, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles all over the land both day and night; they built all our churches, that we have at this day remaining amongſt us, and as many more, which we have razed and pulled down; they founded our univerſities, eſtabliſhed our laws, ſet out tythes and glebe-land for their clergy, built hoſpitals, erected corporations; in a word, did all the good things we found don for our good in this our native kingdom. But now, <hi>Quid agitur in Anglia? Conſulitur de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione.</hi> The former Chriſtians practiſed, and we diſpute; they had a religion, we are ſtill ſeeking one: they exerciſed themſelvs in good works by the guidance of their holy catholik faith which leads to them; all theſe works we by our faith evacuate as menſtruous rags: they had the ſubſtance of true religion in their hearts; we the text in our lips: they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do but to conform their lives to Gods
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57490:49"/>will; all our endeavour is to apply Gods word to our own factions. Sir miſtake me not: The queſtion between us, is not, <hi>whether the people are to have Gods word or no:</hi> but whether that word, conſiſt in the letter left to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples diſpoſal; or in the ſubſtance urgently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon people for their practis. And this becaus you underſtand not, but miſtake the whole buſines, all your talk in this your eighteenth chapter vades into nothing.</p>
               <p>Where <hi>Fiat lux</hi> ſayes in that forenamed <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraff,</hi> that the <hi>Pentateuch</hi> or <hi>hagiography</hi> was never by any High-prieſt among the Jews put into a vulgar tongue, nor the <hi>Goſpell</hi> or <hi>Liturgy</hi> out of greek in the Eaſtern part of the Chriſtian Church, or latin in the Weſtern: You ſlight this diſcours of mine, becaus he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, greek and latin was, ſay you, vulgar tongues themſelvs. I know this well enough. But when and how long ago were they ſo? not for ſom thouſand years to my knowledge. And was the Bible, Pſalms, or Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy then put into vulgar tongues, when thoſe they were firſt writ in, ceaſed to be vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar? This you ſhould have ſpoke to, if you had meant to ſay any thing, or gain-ſay me. Nor is it to purpos, to tell me that S. <hi>Jerom</hi> tranſlated the Bible into <hi>Dalmatian;</hi> I know well enough it has been ſo tranſlated by ſome ſpecial perſons into <hi>Gothiſh, Armenian, Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian,</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:57490:49"/>and other particular dialects. But did the Church either of the Hebrews or Chriſtians, either greek or latin, ever deliver it ſo tranſlated to the generality of people, or uſe it in their ſervice, or command it ſo to be don, as a thing of general concernment and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity? So far is it from that, that they would never permit it. This I ſaid, and I firſt ſaid it, before you ſpoke, and your meer gain-ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further reaſon or probability of proof can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſpoſſeſs me.</p>
               <p>Syrian you would prov not to be any known language in <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> becaus the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple underſtood it not, as appears in the book of <hi>Kings,</hi> where <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> general of the hoſt of <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> when he defied King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> under the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was intreated by the Hebrew princes to ſpeak Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack, and not the Jews language to fright the poor people. But Sir you are miſtaken: for that tongue the princes perſwaded <hi>Rabſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keh</hi> to ſpeak, was the Aſſyrian, his own lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which was learned by the gentry of <hi>Paleſtin,</hi> as we in <hi>England</hi> learn french; which although by abbreviation it be called <hi>Syriack,</hi> yet it differed as much from the Jews language, which was ſpoke by Chriſt and his apoſtles (wherof <hi>Eli, Eli, lama ſabacthani</hi> is part) and was ever ſince that time called ſyrian or ſyriack, as french differs from eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57490:50"/>And if you would read attentively, you may ſuſpect by the very words of the text, that the Jews language even then was not He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew. For it had been a ſhorter and plainer expreſſion, and more anſwerable to their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom ſo to call it, if it had been ſo, than by a paraphraſe to name it the <hi>Jews language;</hi> which if then it was called <hi>Syrian,</hi> as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it was, then had the princes reaſon to call it rather the Jews language then Syrian, becaus that and the Aſſyrian differed more in natur then appellation; though ſom difference doubtles ther was in the very word and name, although tranſlatours have not heeded to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it. <hi>Shibbolet</hi> and <hi>Sibbolet</hi> may differ more in ſignification than ſound; nor is <hi>Brittiſh</hi> and <hi>Brutiſh</hi> ſo near in nature, as they are in name. And who knows not that <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria</hi> were ſeveral kingdoms. As likewiſe were the languages.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Couſins,</hi> now byſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſojourneying in <hi>Paris,</hi> when he underſtood of a grecian byſhops arrival there, did with ſome other engliſh gentlemen in his company give him a viſit, and afterwards with the ſame or like company went frequently to ſee him. The articles of our Engliſh Church were tranſlated into greek, and ſhown him. Many queſtions were asked him about the ſervice of the grecian Church, praying for the dead, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57490:50"/>of Saints, real preſence, confeſſion; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dr. <hi>Couſins</hi> can tell himſelf what anſwer he received from that venerable grave prelate <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> arch-biſhop of <hi>Trapeſond;</hi> for that was his name and title. In brief, he owned not thoſe articles, as any way conſonant to the faith of the Greeks, who beleeved and had ever practiſed the contrary. He alſo told them diſtinctly and openly, that <hi>Maſs</hi> or <hi>Liturgy</hi> was, and had ever been the great work of their Chriſtianity all over the greek Church; that confeſſion of ſins to a prieſt, praying for the dead, invocation of ſaints, and ſuch like points wherein we in <hi>England</hi> differ from papiſts, wer all great parts of their religion, and their conſtant practis. Finally he let them know, that all the Liturgies, both thoſe of S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> S. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> were ever kept in the learned greek, differing from the vulgar language. And withal ſhowed his own greek book of <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which he uſed himſelf at the altar. Dr. <hi>Couſins</hi> did himſelf ſee him officiate with his lay brother a monk of S. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> belonging to S. <hi>Catherins</hi> monaſtery in mount <hi>Sina,</hi> miniſtring to him at the altar; and found both by his words and practis, that in all thoſe and other eſſential parts and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of Chriſtianity the Greeks agreed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly with the Roman Church. This teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Sir, of a venerable arch-byſhop to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57490:51"/>ſuch a worthy perſon as Dr. <hi>Couſins,</hi> might I ſhould think ſuffice to juſtify my words, and make you beleev with me, that Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies have ever been uſed, as <hi>Fiat lux</hi> ſpeaks, in a learned language diſtinct from the vulgar. But we need not go far from home for a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. When was the Bible or Service-book ſeen here in <hi>England</hi> for a thouſand years ſpace in any other language but Latin, before <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt dayes (except haply the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which the Saxons and almoſt all people, have ever had in their own tongue, being a chief part of Chriſtians devotion) or in Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh or Welch, before the byſhop of S. <hi>Aſaph</hi> his tranſlation?</p>
               <p>You mightily inſult over me in your 336 page, for ſaying, that the <hi>bible was kept by the Hebrews in an ark or tabernacle,</hi> not touched by the people, but brought out at times to the prieſt, that he might inſtruct the people out of it. Here, ſay you, the <hi>authour of Fiat lux betrayes his groſs ignorance and ſomthing more: for the ark was placed in ſanctum ſanctorum, and not entered but by the prieſt only once a year, wheras the people were weekly inſtructed.</hi> But Sir, do I ſpeak there of any <hi>ſanctum ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or of any ark in that place? was ther, or could ther be, no more arks but one? If you had been only in theſe latter dayes, in any ſynagogue or convention of Jews, you might
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57490:51"/>have ſeen even now, how the bible is kept ſtill with them in an ark or tabernacle, in imitation of their forefathers, when they have now no <hi>ſanctum ſanctorum</hi> amongſt them. You may alſo diſcern, how according to their cuſtom, they cringe and proſtrate at the bringing out of the Bible, which is the only ſolemn adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion left amongſt them; and that there be more arks than that in <hi>ſanctum ſanctorum.</hi> If I had called it a <hi>box</hi> or <hi>cheſt</hi> or <hi>cuphoard,</hi> you had let it paſs. But I uſed that word as more ſacred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>19</hi> ch. from page <hi>365</hi> to <hi>386.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I diſcerned in your ninteenth chapter which is upon my paragraff of <hi>Communion in one kind</hi> a ſomwhat more then ordinary ſwelling chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; which moved me to look over that my paragraff afreſh. And I found my fault: ther is in it ſo much of Chriſtian reaſon and ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that if I had ſince the time I firſt wrote it, ſwerved from my former judgment, of the probability I conceived to be in that Roman practis of communicating in one kind, I had there met with enough to convert my ſelf. And therfor wondered no more, that you ſhould load me ſo heavily with your wonted imputations of fraud, ignorance, blaſphemy, and the like. I ever perceiv you to be then moſt of all paſſionate, when you meet with moſt convincing reaſons. When the exorciſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:57490:52"/>is moſt innocent, his patient, they ſay, then frets and foams and curſes moſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>20</hi> ch. from page <hi>386</hi> to <hi>402.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Ther is in your twentieth chapter, which proſecutes my paragraff of <hi>Saints or Hero's,</hi> one word of yours, that requires my notice. I ſay in that my paragraff, that the pagans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided the ancient Chriſtians for three of their uſages. Firſt, for <hi>eating their own God:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for <hi>kneeling to their prieſts genitals:</hi> Thirdly, for <hi>worſhipping an aſſes head.</hi> This laſt you except againſt, and impute my ſtory <hi>to my own ſimplicity and ignorance, if not to ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wors; for that imputation,</hi> ſay you, <hi>was not laid upon Chriſtians at all, but only upon Jews, as may be ſeen in</hi> Joſephus. But Sir, you may know, that <hi>in odioſis</hi> the primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were ever numbred among the Jews; and what evil report lay upon theſe, was charged alſo upon them, though ſometimes upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ground. And although <hi>Joſephus</hi> may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Jews, and not the Chriſtians; yet a long while after his time, if not even then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that ſlander was generally all over the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan world charged upon Chriſtians alſo, as may be read in <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and other ancient writers; yea and very probably, by the very Jews themſelvs who bitterly hated them, caſt off from themſelvs upon the poor Chriſtians on another account, which I ſpecified in <hi>Fiat
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57490:52"/>lux.</hi> And through the whole Roman em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire did the ſound of this ſcandal ring up and down, for ſom ages together. Inſomuch that <hi>Tertullian</hi> himſelf conceited, that as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion was derived from the Jews; ſo likewiſe that the imputation of the <hi>aſſes head,</hi> firſt put upon the Jews, might from them be derived upon Chriſtian religion. And the ſame <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his <hi>Apologetick</hi> addes theſe words: <q rend="margQuotes">The calumnies, ſaith he, invented to cry down our religion grew to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of impiety, that not long ago in this very city, a pictur of our God was ſhown by a certain infamous perſon, with the ears of an aſſe and a hoof on one of his feet, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with a gown, and a book in his hand; with this inſcription, <hi>This is Onochoetes the God of Chriſtians.</hi> And he addes, that the Chriſtians in the city, as they were much offended with the impiety; ſo did they not a little wonder at the ſtrange uncouth name the villain had put upon their lord and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</q>
                  <hi>Onochoetes</hi> forſooth, he muſt be called <hi>Onochoetes.</hi> And are not you Sir a ſtrange man, to tell me, p. 393. that what <hi>I ſpeak of this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is notoriouſly fals, nay and that I know it is fals, and that I cannot produce one authentick te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, no not one of any ſuch thing.</hi> But this is but your ordinary confidence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>21</hi> ch. from page <hi>402</hi> to <hi>416.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:57490:53"/>
               <p>I muſt not mervail, that my following para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graff, called <hi>Dirge,</hi> is ſo <hi>wantonly plaid upon,</hi> in your one and twentieth chapter. You think of no body after they are dead; nor does it at all concern you, whether they be in hell, or heaven, or ſom third place, or not at all. But Sir, were not all the ancient monuments of the foundations of our churches, colledges, and chappels in <hi>England</hi> now deſtroyed, you would finde your ſelf with that wretched opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of yours, abſolutely incapable to enter upon any benefice, cure, or employment in this land. But the times are changed, and you have nothing now to do, but to eat, drink, and preach; for to morrow you ſhall dye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>22</hi> ch. from page <hi>416 </hi>to <hi>435</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your two and twentieth chapter, which is of the <hi>Pope,</hi> you do but only repeat my words, and not underſtand, and deny, and laugh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>23</hi> ch. from page <hi>435</hi> to Finis.</head>
               <p>Your laſt chapter is upon my paragraff of <hi>Popery,</hi> wherein I ſet down eleven other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of catholik profeſſion, all of them inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, unblamable and ſacred. You onely bite at <hi>the firſt of them,</hi> and having it ſeems enough filled your ſelf with that, your wearied bones go to reſt.</p>
               <p>With <hi>Mas comedido,</hi> the title of my laſt paragraff you meddle not at all: It is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57490:53"/>to you who underſtand not the Engliſh word <hi>Meſſach,</hi> another Gnoſtick <hi>Paldabaoth.</hi> But I would you had <hi>Mas comedido</hi> by heart.</p>
               <p>You cannot but mervail, that I have taken ſo little notice all this while, of your onely one ſtrong and potent Argument, you ſtout <hi>Achilles</hi> that meets me in every paragraff and period, and beats me back into the walls of <hi>Troy.</hi> Wberever I am, whatſoever I ſay, your <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is upon me. All the diſcours of my whole one and thirty para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffs, is by it fell'd to the ground, miſerably bruiſed and battered with that one and the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But I hope you will have me excuſed. I have not leiſur; I am not willing; I want ability to anſwer it, or give you any correſponding ſatisfaction. <hi>The like to our Authour for flouriſhing empty words and cunning ſleights of ſubtilty hath been ſeldom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Here our Authour falls into a great miſadventure,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Here our Authour diſcovers not only his groſs ignorance, but ſomthing more,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour beleeves not a word of all this, nor can,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We finde our Authour never to fail ſo palpably and groſly, as when,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Our Authour ſpeaks notoriouſly fals, nor hath he,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Our Authours hiſtory, philoſophy and reaſon all alike,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Our Authour ſpeaks boldly, though he know it is not ſo, but.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Our Authour, if I could com to ſpeak to him, would not own any of this.</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57490:54"/>
                  <hi>Never any ſuch cunning diſſembling hypocrite as our Authour,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It is no mervail our Authour ſhould ſtill fail both in philoſophy antiquity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who hath not,</hi> &amp;c. In theſe and ſuch like argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which occur almoſt as oft as the pages of your book, you rout <hi>Our Authour</hi> utterly. I am in all this not able to ſay bough to a gooſe. Although I be not conſcious of any ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fraud in my breaſt, or fault in my book, or lye in either; yet in all ſuch talk you muſt, and will, and ſhall have both the firſt and laſt word too.</p>
               <p>Another argument of yours expreſt in twenty places of your Animadverſions, by which you would diſſipate at once great part of <hi>Fiat lux</hi> into the air, does as finely cant, as this does courſly defy. <hi>The religion,</hi> ſay you, <hi>that is now profeſt in England, is that and only that which was firſt in ancient times received here,</hi> &amp;c. This you ſpeak, and the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently do you ſpeak it, the leſs ſignificant you know your words be, and yet ſounding well enough for your deſign. What do you mean I pray you Sir, by <hi>that religion that is now profeſt in England?</hi> Why do you not ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify it? Speak it in down-right language. Is it <hi>Popery</hi> that has been peaceably profeſt in the land for almoſt a thouſand years, and did all the good things we now finde in it; as yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by ſom? No, this you will deny. Is it <hi>prelate-proteſtancy</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:57490:54"/>that for threeſcore years oppreſt popery here? This if you had ſaid, you had praiſed that too much, which your ſelf ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves not. Is it <hi>Presbytery</hi> that warred the laſt twenty years, and utterly deſtroyed the foreſaid Proteſtancy? In ſaying this you had to your own danger diſabled the Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church, now to the great heart-burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Presbyterians eſtabliſht again by law. Is it <hi>Independency</hi> that for ſix or ſeven years curbed the Presbyterian here, in —Tectour <hi>Olivers</hi> time, and had almoſt paſt an Act for the aboliſhing of the three P.P.P. Papiſh, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and Presbyterian. Is it <hi>Quakery,</hi> that is now far enough ſpread, and openly profeſt by many, and judges the Papiſt ſtark naught, the Proteſtant half rotten, the Presbyterian quarter addle, and other Independents imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Is it ſom general <hi>abſtracted religion</hi> that is common to them all? Then Popery as well as any other may be juſtly ſtiled the religion here firſt received. For that common notion in whatever you ſhall ſay it conſiſts, ſo it be poſitive as it ought to be, will be found firſt and principally in the Papiſts faith. But this you have not thought good your ſelf to expres, that you may ſeem to expres ſomthing, that may be thought good to your ſelf, and ill to me. But you muſt deal candidly with me: I am an old ox that hath fixed his foot firmly, and am
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:57490:55"/>not to be out-braved either with your canting words or paſſionate execrations.</p>
               <p>I had told you Sir, of all your tricks from page to page in particular, if nothing had been required at my hands to write, but only my own reply: but being, if I ſhould do ſo, obliged to ſet down your talk too, I think it not worth either my charge or labour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon you ſuch your voluminous imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies. And I have I aſſure you taken notice of all in your book, that may ſeem to have any appearance of reaſon in it (though really ther be none at all againſt me) and is not either ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly untrue, or abſolutely improper. This is all.</p>
               <p>And now good Sir, I could wiſh you had given me the firſt letter of your name; that I might have known how to ſalute you. I have been told of late, that the Authour of the <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon <hi>Fiat lux</hi> is one Doctour <hi>O N,</hi> a Proteſtant againſt Popery which you found down, a Presbyterian againſt Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which you threw down, an Independent againſt Presbyterianry which you kept down. But whether you be Doctour <hi>O N,</hi> or, to turn your inſide outwards, you be <hi>N O</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour; ſince I cannot be aſſured, it ſhall be all one to me. All that I undertook at this time is to let you know, who ever you be, that I have read over your <hi>Animadverſions</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:57490:55"/>my <hi>Fiat lux.</hi> And I thank you for your book; for it confirms my <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> and all the whole deſign of it, I think irrefragably. It ſhows to the eye and really verrifies by your own example, what <hi>Fiat lux</hi> did but ſpeak in words: namely that controverſies of religion are endles for want of ſome one thing to fix upon, which may not be depraved; that they are fraught with uncharitable animoſities, which darken the underſtanding and deprave good manners; that they are mutable as mens fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies be, which can never be fixedly ſtated, ſith every man hath a ſpirit, hath a method, hath an opinion of his own, and ſayes and denyes with endles diverſity; that they are guileful and deluſory, ſometimes fals on both ſides, ever on one, and yet ſtill made out with ſubtil words, ſo plauſible to the eye and ear, that men employed in the multitude of affairs and troubles of this world, can never be able to disintangle thoſe knots of <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con;</hi> then eſpecially at a loſs, when they conſider, that ſuch as mannage thoſe diſputes are all of them intereſted perſons; fiftly that they are mad and irrational, while all parties pretend one and the ſame rule of holy ſcriptur, and yet will admit of no exteriour viſible judg in their viſible exteriour conteſts: laſtly that they are miſchievous and fatal to all places where they riſe: as they have been of late to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:57490:56"/>this our diſtreſſed kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> where diſputes and controverſies about reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion raiſed to a height, by the inferiour ſcribes againſt their prelates, drew after them pikes and guns to make them good, for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years together, with much deſolation and ruin; which times I think I may not unjuſtly call the <hi>Vicars Wars.</hi> For the inferiour Prieſts and Levites, envying the dignities, glory and revenues of their prelates, when they could not otherwiſe get them into their own hands, by their lamentable tones in <hi>Eloimi,</hi> raiſed up the people of the land, to further their deſign. This trick of theirs they learned from wolves. For theſe, when they ſpy a waifaring man whom they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and yet by a narrow ſearch perceiv him to be too ſtrong for them, ſtarting aſide up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſom <hi>hillock,</hi> there ſet upon their tails, they <hi>howl</hi> for help.</p>
               <p>And if any will not beleev <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> that ſuch be the fruits of diſputes and controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and ſuch their nature and <hi>genius,</hi> let them beleev the Authour of <hi>Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> who as he ſayes what he pleaſes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies what he liſts; ſo to his frequent reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, villifications and ſlanders he adjoyns his own menaces of terrour, to make my words good, and juſtify <hi>Fiat lux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You frequently threaten me, that if I write
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:57490:56"/>again I ſhalt <hi>hear more,</hi> far more than you have ſaid in your <hi>Animadverſions:</hi> but I promis you Sir, if you write again, you ſhall never hear more from me. For now the flies begin to com into my chamber, which may haply ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect I ſhould heed their flight and hearken to their buzz, and I muſt not leav thoſe greater employments to look upon your <hi>Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> or any your other books.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Epiſtolae</hi> my only daughter, coms as you ſee to chide you Sir for abuſing her inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Brother. But ſhe does it ſo ſparingly and with ſo many bluſhes, as though the blame wer hers, though yours be the miſdemeanour. And I hope ſhe may ſo far work upon your good natur, if you have any left, that laying your hand upon your heart you may now ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing ſay, <hi>Quid feci? I have wronged the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</hi> And for that end I wiſh you all grace and peace; and I wiſh it you with all my heart, who am natural father both of that innocent boy <hi>Fiat lux,</hi> and of this <hi>Epiſtola</hi> his ſiſter; and if you will but reckon me ſo, your very true friend</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JVC.</signed>
                  <date>Given this <hi>V.</hi> of the <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>April</hi> in the year of our Lord MDCLXIII.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:57490:57"/>
            <head>The places of my Paragraffs in this Epiſtle.</head>
            <list>
               <item>DIverſity of feuds <hi>page 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ground of quarrels <hi>page 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nullity of title <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Heats and reſolutions <hi>page 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Motives of moderation <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſcurity of God <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Darknes of nature <hi>page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Myſtery of providence <hi>page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Help <hi>page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reaſon <hi>page 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Light and Spirit <hi>page 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Plea of parties <hi>page 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Scriptur <hi>page 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hiſtory of religion <hi>page 72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcovery <hi>page 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meſſach <hi>page 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Virgin <hi>Mary page 83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Images or Figurs <hi>page 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tongues or latin ſervice <hi>page 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Table or Communion <hi>page 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saints or Hero's <hi>page 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dirge <hi>page 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pope <hi>page 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Popery <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mas comedido <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:57490:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
